<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the adoration of the host, as it is taught and practiced in the Church of Rome wherein an answer is given to T.G. on that subject, and to Monsieur Boileau's late book De adoratione eucharistiæ, Paris 1685.</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588032</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the adoration of the host, as it is taught and practiced in the Church of Rome wherein an answer is given to T.G. on that subject, and to Monsieur Boileau's late book De adoratione eucharistiæ, Paris 1685.</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Payne. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 66.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Boileau, Jacques, 1635-1716. --  De adoratione Eucharistiae.</term>
               <term>Godden, Thomas, 1624-1688.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Adoration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the ADORATION OF THE HOST, As it is Taught and Practiced in the CHURCH of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein an Anſwer is given to <hi>T. G.</hi> on that Subject, And to Monſieur <hi>Boileau</hi>'s late book <hi>De Adoratione Euchariſtiae. Paris</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons,</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63797:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63797:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF THE ADORATION of the HOST, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>IDolatry</hi> is ſo great a Blot in any Church, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other glorious <hi>Marks</hi> it may pretend to, that it is not to be wondred, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is very angry to be charged with it, as it has always been by all the <hi>Reform'd;</hi> who have given in this among many others, as a juſt and neceſſary Reaſon of their Reformation; and it muſt be confeſſed to be ſo, if it be fully and clearly made good againſt it; and if it be not, it muſt be owned to be great Uncharitableneſs on the other ſide, which is no good <hi>Note</hi> of a Church nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; a grievous Slander and moſt uncharitable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, which will fall eſpecially upon all the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who by their Conſent and Subſcription to its Articles and to the Doctrine of its Homilies, and to the Book of Common-Prayer, do expreſly join in it. For it is not the private Opinion only of ſome particular and forward men in their Zeal and Heat againſt Popery, thus to accuſe it of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> but it is the deliberate, and ſober, and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63797:3"/>
               <hi>Charge</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of which no honeſt man can be a Member, and a Miniſter, who does not make and believe it. I might give ſeveral Inſtances to ſhew this; but ſhall only mention one, wherein I have undertaken to defend our Church in its charge of Idolatry upon the Papiſts, in their <hi>Adoration</hi> of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> which is in its Declaration about Kneeling at the Sacrament after the Office of the Communion, in which are theſe remarkable words, <hi>It is hereby declared, that no Adoration is intended, or ought to be done, either unto the ſacramental Bread and Wine there bodily received, or unto any corporal preſence of Chriſts natural Fleſh and Blood; for the ſacramental Bread and Wine remain ſtill in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſubſtances, and therefore may not be adored, for that were Idolatry to be abhorred of all faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> Here it moſt plainly declares its mind againſt that, which is the Ground and Foundation of their Worſhipping the Hoſt, That the Elements do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their natural Subſtances after Conſecration; if they do remain, as we and all Proteſtants hold, even the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> then in Worſhipping the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Elements, they worſhip meer Creatures, and are by their own Confeſſion guilty of Idolatry, as I ſhall ſhow by and by; and if <hi>Chriſt's natural Fleſh and Blood be not corporally preſent there,</hi> neither with the Subſtance, nor Signs of the Elements, then the Adoring what is there, muſt be the Adoring ſome things elſe than Chriſts body; and if Bread on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be there, and they adore that which is there, they muſt ſurely adore the Bread it ſelf, in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our Church; but I ſhall afterwards ſtate the Controverſie more exactly between us. Our Church has here taken notice of the true Iſſue of it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that to be falſe, and that it is both Unfit and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63797:3"/>Idolatrous too, to Worſhip the Elements upon any account after Conſecration, and it continued of the ſame mind, and expreſt it as particularly, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Canons of 1640, where it ſays<note n="a" place="margin">Canon 7. 1640. about placing the Communion Table under this head, <hi>A Declaration about ſome Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi>
               </note>, That <hi>for the cauſe of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try committed in the Maſs, all Popiſh Altars were demoliſht;</hi> ſo that none can more fully charge them with Idolatry in this point, than our Church has done.</p>
            <p>It recommends at the ſame time, but with great Temper and Moderation, the religious Geſture of bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards the Altar, both before and out of the time of Celebration of the Holy Euchariſt, and in it, and in neither<note n="a" place="margin">Ib. Cant 7. 1640.</note>, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon any opinion of a corporal preſence of Chriſt on the Holy Table, or in the myſtical Elements;</hi> but only to give outward and bodily, as well as inward Worſhip to the Divine Majeſty; and it commands all Perſons to receive the Sacrament Kneeling<note n="b" place="margin">Rubric at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note>, in a poſture of Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Primitive Church uſed to do, with the greateſt Expreſſion of Reverence and Humility, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> ſpeaks<note n="c" place="margin">Cyril. Hieroſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lym. Catech. Myſtag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, and as I ſhall ſhew, is the meaning of the greateſt Authorities they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce out of the Ancients for Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not <hi>to,</hi> but <hi>at</hi> the Sacrament; ſo far are we from any unbecoming, or irreverent u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of that Myſtery, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Controv. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</note>, when he is angry with thoſe, who will not Worſhip it, tells them out of <hi>Optatus,</hi> that the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> gave it to Dogs; and out of <hi>Victor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ticenſis,</hi> that the <hi>Arrians</hi> trod it under their Feet;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63797:4"/>that we ſhould abhor any ſuch diſreſpect ſhown to the ſacred Symbols of our Saviours Body, as is uſed by them, in throwing it into the Flames to quench a Fire, or into the Air, or Water to ſtop a Tempeſt, or Inundation, or keep themſelves from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or any the like miſcheif (to prevent which they will throw away even the God they Worſhip) or the putting it to any the like undecent Superſtitions. 'Tis out of the great Honour and Reſpect that we bear to the Sacrament, that we are againſt the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying it up and down as a ſhow, and the Expoſing and Proſtituting it to ſo ſhameful an Abuſe, and ſo groſs an Idolatry. We give very great Reſpect and Reverence to all things that relate to God, and are ſet apart to his Worſhip and Service; to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple where God is ſaid himſelf to dwell, and to be more immediately preſent; to the Altar whereon the Myſteries of Chriſts Body and Blood are ſolemnly celebrated; to the Holy Veſſels, that are always uſed in thoſe Adminiſtrations; to the Holy Bible, which is the Word of God, and the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as the Sacrament is his Body, and the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> in his Blood; to the Font, which is the Laver of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, wherein we put on Chriſt, as well as we eat him in the Euchariſt; and if we would ſtrain things, and pick out of the Ancient and Devout Chriſtians what is ſaid of all theſe, it would go as far, and look as like to adoring them, as what with all their care they collect and produce for adoring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as I ſhall afterwards make appear, in Anſwer to what the<note n="a" place="margin">Jacob. Boileau Pariſ. De Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Euchariſtiae. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ. <hi>1685.</hi>
               </note> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Defender of the Adoration of the Euchariſt, has culled, or rather raked together out of the Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63797:4"/>
It ſeems from that Declaration of our Church, that ſome were either ſo <hi>ſilly,</hi> or ſo <hi>ſpiteful,</hi> as to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that by our Kneeling at the Sacrament, we gave Worſhip to the Elements; and that learned man is willing to have it believed, that we do thereby, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternè Euchariſtiam colere</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boil.</hi> p. 145.</note>, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Worſhip the Sacrament, and he blames us for not doing it inwardly in our minds, as well as out wardly with our Bodies; ſo willing are theſe men to joyn with our wildeſt Diſſenters in their unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Charges againſt our Church, and uſe any crutches that may help their own weak Cauſe, or be made uſe of to ſtrike at us; but it may as well be ſaid, that the Diſſenters Worſhip their Cuſhions, or their Seats, when they kneel before them; the roof of the Church, or the crowns of their Hats, when they fix their Eyes upon them, at the ſame time they are at Prayers upon their Knees; or that the Papiſts worſhip the Prieſt himſelf, before whom they Kneel in their Confeſſions; or that on <hi>Aſhwedneſday</hi> they adore the holy Aſhes as they call them, and on <hi>Palm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday</hi> the holy Boughs, which they do not pretend to do, becauſe they Kneel when they are given them; as well as that we Worſhip the Euchariſt, or the Myſtical Elements, when we receive them Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and diſavow any ſuch thing, and declare it to <hi>be Idolatry to be abhorr'd of all faithful Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is it Idolatry to Worſhip Chriſt? Or to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Body of Chriſt, tho not for it ſelf, yet for the ſake of the Divine Nature, to which it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hypoſtatically united? No, by no means; I know no Hereticks, tho they denied Chriſts Divinity, but yet were for Worſhipping him; the old <hi>Arrians,</hi> and the late <hi>Socinians;</hi> but how juſtifiably, when they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63797:5"/>believe him but a meer man, or only a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Creature; they and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are both concerned to defend, and to clear it, if they can of Idolatry. As to the Worſhip of the Fleſh, tho <hi>Neſtorius</hi> could not do this according to his Principles, as St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> and the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> argue againſt him; nor could the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of old; yet I know none but ſome of their School-men diſpute now of Adoring the Fleſh or Humane Nature of Chriſt, which however it be in our minds, is never in truth abſtracted from his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. But we will not at all trouble our ſelves with thoſe parts of the Science of controverſie; nor ſhall we ſtand upon any of thoſe things. Well then, why may not Chriſt and his Body be adored in the Sacrament, if they are proper Objects of Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. No doubt but they may be adored in this <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> too, and in all the Offices of the Chriſtian Religion, wherein we pray to Chriſt, and Kneel before him, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the devout acts of the mind toward him, put our truſt and hope in him, and expect Salvation from him, and devote our ſelves in all Subjection to him, and bow both our Souls and our Bodies, and give all, both internal and external Worſhip to him; this Adoration we give to Chriſt, who is God bleſſed for ever, and who ſits at the right hand of God the Father. And the very ſame the Papiſts give to the Sacrament, to the Hoſt, and the conſecrated Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the moſt Sovereign, and Abſolute, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Degree of Religious Worſhip that is due to God, whoſe creatures thoſe Elements are; or to Chriſt himſelf, who commanded us to receive them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him. But it is only Chriſt, ſay they, whom we Worſhip in the Sacrament, whom we adore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63797:5"/>as being preſent there with his Body in the Hoſt, and not the Hoſt or the Sacrament it ſelf; ſo a great many of them would fain bring off the matter, or at leaſt colour and diſguiſe it; <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. 4.</hi> de Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt <hi>c. 29.</hi> Quicquid ſit de modo loquendi, ſtatus quaeſtionis non eſt, niſi an Chriſtus in Euchariſtia ſit adorandus cultu la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae.</note>, when he had entangled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the diſtinctions of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Sacrament, whether formally or materially; would extri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate himſelf, by thus ſtating the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and reducing it to this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Whether Chriſt be to be adored in the Euchariſt?</hi> And St. <hi>Clara</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>St. Clara</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Natura, Gratia, <hi>p. 308.</hi> Nota bene, non dicit Concilium Tridentinum, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, ſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum in Sacramento, latria adorandum.</note> would reconcile the diſpute with this Obſervation, <hi>Nota benè. Mark this, the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>does not ſay, that the Sacrament is to be adored, but Chriſt in the Sacrament.</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo great a man as <hi>Caſſander</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Adoratio non ad exterius ſignum quod exterius vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed ad ipſam rem &amp; veritatem quae interius credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur referenda, <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</hi> Conſult. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorat. Euchar.</note>, ſhould ſay, Unleſs, with a deſign to condemn the thing, <hi>That the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is not to be given to the outward ſign which is ſeen; but is to be referr'd to the thing it ſelf, and to that which is truly and inwardly believed.</hi> But Reconcilers, who will attempt the vain project of Accommodation, muſt do with the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Apelles</hi> did with <hi>Antigonus</hi> his face, they muſt draw but one part, but half of it, that ſo they may Artificially conceal its deformed, and its blind ſide. That all theſe do ſo, I ſhall ſhow by ſtating the Controverſie carefully and truly, which is the chiefeſt thing in this diſpute; for they love to hide their own Doctrines as much as they can; and they cunningly contrive moſt of them with a back door, to ſlip out at privately and upon occaſion.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63797:6"/>The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has in this, as in other things, uſed art, and not ſpoke out in one place, as it does in another; that ſo we may miſtake half its words for its full meaning, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others were willing to do, or at leaſt to have others do ſo. In its ſixth Canon on the Euchariſt it only ſays<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Trident. Can. 6.</hi> De Euchar. ſi quis dixerit in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto Euchariſtiae Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Chriſtum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nigenitum Dei fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium non eſſe cultu Latriae etiam exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no adorandum, ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit.</note>, <hi>If any one ſhall ſay, that Chriſt the only begotten Son of God is not to be adored with the external Worſhip of</hi> Latria, <hi>in the holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, let him be accurſed.</hi> Who will not ſay in thoſe general words, that Chriſt is to be adored with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward Worſhip both, not only in the Holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, but of Baptiſm too, and in every Chriſtian Office, and in every Prayer, and ſolemn Invocation of him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publick or private? But they mean a great deal more than all this, by Worſhipping Chriſt in the Sacrament, and in as plain words they ſay<note n="b" place="margin">Ib. <hi>13.</hi> Seſſ. e. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, That the Sacrament it ſelf is to be adored; that, whatever it be which is ſomething beſides Chriſt, even according to them, which is placed in the Patin, and upon the Altar, which the Prieſt holds in his hands, and lifts up to be ſeen, this very thing is to be adored; <hi>There is no doubt,</hi> ſays the Council<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> Nullus dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi locus relinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quin omnes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti fideles pro more in Catholica Eccleſia ſemper recepto, latriae cultum qui vero Deo debetur, <hi>huic ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſimo</hi> Sacramento in Veneratione adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant; neque enim minus eſt adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quod fuerit a Chriſto Domino at ſumatur, inſtitutum.</note>, <hi>but that all faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, according to the cuſtom always received in the Catholick Church, ought to give Supreme and Sovereign Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is due to God himſelf, to the moſt Holy Sacrament in their Worſhip of it; for it is never the leſs to be adored, tho it was inſtituted of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63797:6"/>Chriſt to be received.</hi> That which is to be <hi>received,</hi> which is to be put into the Peoples Mouths by the Prieſt (for ſince they have made a God of the Sacrament, they will not truſt the People to feed themſelves with it, nor take it into their hands; and they may with as much reaſon in time not think fit that they ſhould eat it) this which was appointed of Chriſt to be taken and eaten as a Sacrament; this is now to ſerve for another uſe, to be <hi>adored</hi> as a God; and it would be as true Hereſie in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not to ſay, that the <hi>Sacrament of the Altar</hi> is to be adored, as not to ſay, that <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> is to be adored. But what according to them is this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? It is the remaining Species of Bread and Wine, and the natural Body and Blood of Chriſt, inviſibly, yet carnally preſent under them; and theſe together make up <hi>one entire Object of their Adoration,</hi> which they call <hi>Sacramentum;</hi> for Chriſts body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Species, and Accidents at leaſt of Bread and Wine, would not according to them be a Sacrament; they being the outward and viſible part, are,<note place="margin">Lombard. ſent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> according to their School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, properly and ſtrictly called the <hi>Sacramentum,</hi> and the other the <hi>res Sacramenti;</hi> and to this external part of the Sacrament, as well as to the internal, they give <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and Adoration; to theſe remaining Species, which be they what they will, are but Creatures; religious Worſhip is given toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Chriſts Body, and they with that, are the whole formal Object of their Adoration. Non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Chriſtum ſed Totum viſibile Sacramentum, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co cultu adorari, <hi>ſays</hi> Suarez<note n="a" place="margin">In Th. Quaeſt. <hi>79.</hi> diſp.</note>, quia eſt unum conſtans ex Chriſto &amp; Speciebus; <hi>Not only Chriſt, but the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63797:7"/>whole viſible Sacrament</hi> (which muſt be ſomething beſides Chriſts inviſible Body) <hi>is to be adored with one and the ſame Worſhip, becauſe it is one thing</hi> (or one Object) <hi>conſiſting of Chriſt and the Species.</hi> So ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their learned men<note n="b" place="margin">Henriquez. <hi>Moral,</hi> l. 8. c. 32.</note>, Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebus Euchariſtiae datur Latria prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſtum quem continent; <hi>The higheſt Worſhip is given to the Species of the Euchariſt, becauſe of Chriſt, whom they contain.</hi> Now Chriſt, whom they contain, muſt be ſomething elſe than the Species that contain him. Let him be preſent never ſo truly and ſubſtantially in the Sacrament, or under the Species, he cannot be ſaid to be the ſame thing with that in which he is ſaid to be preſent; and as ſubtil as they are, and as thin and ſubtil as theſe Species are, they can never get off from Idolatry upon their own Principles in their Worſhipping of them; and they can never be left out, but muſt be part of the whole which is to be adored, <hi>totum illud quod ſimul adoratur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>de Euch.</hi> l. 4. c. 30.</note> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls it, muſt include theſe as well as Chriſts Body. Adorationem, <hi>ſaies</hi> Bellarmine<note n="a" place="margin">Bellarmine <hi>de Euch.</hi> l. 4. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note>, ad Symbola etiam panis &amp; vini pertine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ut quod unum cum ipſo Chriſto quem continent, <hi>Adoration belongs even to the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols of Bread and Wine, as they are apprehended to be one with Chriſt whom they contain;</hi> and ſo make up one entire Object of Worſhip with him, and may be Worſhipt together with Chriſt, as <hi>T. G.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cathol. no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, <hi>p.</hi> 268.</note> owns in his Anſwer to his moſt learned Adverſary; and are the very term of Adoration, as <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Idol.</hi> l. 2. c. 5.</note> ſays, who further adds, that they who think this Worſhip does not at all belong to the Species,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63797:7"/>in that heretically oppoſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual cuſtomand ſence of the Church.<note place="margin">Qui cenſeunt nullo modo ad Species ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eam Veneratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pertinere, in eo Haeretice pugnare contra perpetuum uſum &amp; ſenſum Eccleſiae: de Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerati one Sacram. ad Artic. <hi>Thom. 5.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed they ſay, That theſe Species or Accidents, are not to be Worſhipt for themſelves, or upon their own account, but becauſe Chriſt is preſent in them, and under them; and ſo they may be Worſhipt as <hi>T. G.</hi> ſays<note n="d" place="margin">Ib.</note>, <hi>with Chriſt in like manner, as his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were Worſhipt together with him</hi> upon Earth; which is a ſimilitude taken out of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> the Magazine not only of Arguments and Authorities, but of Similitudes too, it ſeems, which are to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that Church; <hi>Quemadmodum</hi> ſaies he<note n="e" place="margin">de Euch. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat.</note>, <hi>qui Chriſtum in terris ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitum adorabant, non ipſum ſolum ſed etiam veſtes quodam modo adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi> And are Chriſts Carments then to be Worſhipt with <hi>Latria,</hi> as well as Chriſt himſelf, or as the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? I think they will not ſay this of any of the Relicks they have of Chriſt, or his clothes: Did they, who Worſhipt Chriſt when he was upon the Earth, worſhip his clothes too? Did the Wiſe men worſhip the blankets, the clouts, and the ſwadling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloths, as well as the bleſſed Babe lying in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Might it not as well be ſuppoſed that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worſhipt the Aſs, upon which Chriſt rode; not for himſelf, but for the ſake, and upon the account of Chriſt, who was upon him; as that they worſhipt his clothes, or his Sandals on which he trod, or the Garments which he wore? <hi>Bellarmines quodammodo adorabant,</hi> ſhews his heart miſgave him, and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63797:8"/>he was ſenſible the Similitude would not do, when he uſed it; but <hi>T. G.</hi> is a man of more heart and courage, or front at leaſt, and he found the cauſe was in great need of it, and ſo he ſaies boldly, without any trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>quodammodo,</hi> that they worſhipt his Garments.</p>
            <p>The humane Nature it ſelf of Chriſt, conſidered alone, and being a meer Creature, is not an object of Worſhip, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaies<note n="a" place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi> Serm. <hi>58.</hi> De verbis Dom. Si natura Deus non eſt filius ſed Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, nec colendus eſt omnino nec ut Deus Adorandus. Ego Dominicam car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, imo perfectam in Chriſto humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem propterea ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, quod a divinitate ſuſcepta atque Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati unita eſt,— Denique ſi hominem ſeparaveris a Deo, ut Photinus, vel Paulus Samoſatenus, illi ego nunquam credo nec ſervio.</note>, but only as it is hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically united to the Divine Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo intimately and vitally united to it, as to make one Perſon with it, with God himſelf, one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo one Object of Worſhip; and if the Sacramental Symbols or Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, are to be adored with true <hi>latria,</hi> not <hi>per ſe,</hi> or upon their own account, but by reaſon of the intimate Union and Conjunction which they have with Chriſt, as they ſay, not only with Chriſts body, for that alone is not to be worſhipt, much leſs another thing that is united to it; but with Chriſts Perſon, and then there muſt be as many Perſons of Chriſt, as there are conſecrated Wafers; then theſe Species being thus worſhipt upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that Chriſts humanity is, as <hi>Gregory de Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> owns they muſt, [<hi>This Worſhip,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>belongs after a certain manner to the ſpecies, as when the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is worſhipt in the humanity which he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the Divine Worſhip belongs alſo to the created Humanity.</hi> Pertinet per accidens ſuo quodam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ea veneratio ad Species, quemadmodum ſuo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, etiam hoc ipſo quod adoratur Divinum verbum in humanitate aſſumptâ pertinet ejuſmodi Divinus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63797:8"/>cultus, ad illam humanitatem creatam ſecundario, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in hoc eſt aliqua Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria.]<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valentia,</hi> Diſput. <hi>6.</hi> Queſt. <hi>11.</hi> de ritu &amp; oblat. Euchariſt.</note> muſt be alſo united to Chriſt, the ſame way that his Humanity is united to his Divinity, ſo as to become with that, one entire object of Worſhip, as the Species are, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them, with Chriſt in the Euchariſt; that is, they muſt become one <hi>ſuppoſitum,</hi> or one Perſon with Chriſt. This is ſo weighty a difficulty, as makes the greateſt <hi>Atlas</hi>'s of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweat, by ſink under it. <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Idol.</hi> l. 2. c. 5.</note> owns the wonderful Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the Species have with Chriſt, but denies their being hypoſtatically united to him; but then, how are they to be worſhipt? Since it is owned by him and the Schoolmen, that the very Humanity of Chriſt is to be worſhipt only upon the account of its hypoſtatical Union; and tho God be very nearly and intimately preſent in other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet they are not to be worſhipt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that preſence, becauſe they do not make one <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi> or <hi>hypoſtaſis</hi> with him, or are not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatically united to him. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> being pincht on this ſide, removes the burden to t'other, that is as ſore, and can as little bear it; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſays he,<note n="b" place="margin">Longe a liter eſt Chriſtus in Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtia, &amp; in aliis rebus Deus; Nam in Euchariſtia unum tautum Suppofitum eſt, idque Divinum, caeteraque omnia ad illud pertinent, &amp; cum illo unum quid faciunt, licet non eodem modo, <hi>Bellar. de Euch.</hi> l. 4. c. 30.</note> 
               <hi>is much</hi> otherwiſe <hi>in the Euchariſt, than God is in other things; for in the Euchariſt, there is but one only</hi> ſuppoſitum, <hi>and that Divine; all other things there preſent belong to, and make one thing with that.</hi> If they do ſo, then ſure they are hypoſtatically united with Chriſt, as <hi>T. G</hi>'s. learned Adverſary charges upon <hi>Bellarmine</hi> from this place; if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63797:9"/>they make but one <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi> with him, and but one with him, let it be in what manner it will, they muſt be hypoſtatically united to him. <hi>Bellarmines Licet non eodem modo,</hi> tho not <hi>after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> is both unintelligible, and will not at all help the matter; 'tis only a Confeſſion from him, that at the ſame time that he ſays they are hypoſtatically united to Chriſt, and make one <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi> with him, and one object of Worſhip, that he does not know how this can be, and that his thoughts are in a great ſtreight about it, ſo that he doubts they are not hypoſtatically united at the ſame time that he yet ſaies they are ſo; for this is no way impoſed upon him, as <hi>T. G.</hi> ſaies, notwithſtanding his <hi>non eodem modo.</hi> If in the Incarnation of Chriſt, one ſhould ſay, That the Soul and Body of Chriſt are both united to his Divinity, but that both were not united after the ſame manner; but the Soul in ſuch a manner, as being a Spirit, and the Body in another; yet ſo, that both made but one <hi>Suppoſitum</hi> with it, and that Divine; and that all his humane Nature belong'd to that, and made one with that, tho not after the ſame manner; would not this be ſtill an owning the hypoſtatical Union between Chriſts Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and his Soul and Body? and ſo muſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be between Chriſts Divinity, and his Body, and the Species; if they make one <hi>Suppoſitum,</hi> and are, as they hold, to be worſhipt as ſuch.</p>
            <p>Thus I have taken care to give you their Doctrine, and ſtate the Caſe with ſome exactneſs; tho I am ſenſible, with too much length; but that is the way to ſhorten the Controverſie; and by this means I have cut off their common retreats, and ſtopt up thoſe little lurking holes they generally run to, and in which they are wont to Earth themſelves. As, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63797:9"/>they worſhip only Chriſt in the Sacrament, or Chriſt under the accidents of Bread and Wine; and that 'tis only Chriſt, or the Body of Chriſt with which his Divinity is always preſent, is the formal object of their Adoration in the Sacrament, and that their Worſhip is given to that, and not to the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Elements, or to the remaining Species of Bread and Wine; it appears from their own Doctrine and Principles to be quite otherwiſe; and if we take them at their own words, they are ſufficient to bear witneſs againſt them, and condemn them of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but this will be found to be much greater and groſſer, when the whole foundation of this Doctrine of theirs of the Worſhip of the Hoſt, proves upon Examination to be falſe, and one of the moſt thick and unreaſonable Errors in the World, to wit, the belief of Tranſubſtantiation, or that the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament, are converted into the natural and ſubſtantial Body and Blood of Chriſt, ſo that there remains nothing of the ſubſtance of the Bread and Wine after Conſecration, but only the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt corporally preſent, under the Species and Accidents of Bread and Wine. If this Doctrine be true, it will in great meaſure diſcharge them from the guilt of Idolatry; for then their only fault will be their joyning the Species, which how thin and ghoſtly ſoever they be, yet are Creatures, together with Chriſt, as one Object of Worſhip; and unleſs they alter their Doctrine on this point, from what it is now, I ſee not how they can juſtifie their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the Worſhip due only to God, not only the adorable ſubſtance of Chriſts Body, but the very Veils and Symbols under which they ſuppoſe that to lye; and yet when they teach, as they do, the adoring of the Sacrament,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63797:10"/>they muſt adore the viſible and outward part of it, as well as the inviſible Body of Chriſt; for without the remaining Species, it would not, according to them, be a Sacrament; and they have not gone ſo far yet, I think, as to deny that there are any remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Species, and that our ſenſes do ſo far wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, that when we ſee ſomething, there is really nothing of a viſible Object. And the ſame Object which is <hi>viſible,</hi> is <hi>adorable</hi> too, according to them: If Chriſts Body were ſubſtantially preſent in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho it were lawful to adore it as there preſent; but by no means, either the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> or <hi>Species</hi> of Bread <hi>with it;</hi> yet it is much to be doubted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were a duty, or neceſſary to do ſo. It would be preſent ſo like a Prince in <hi>Incognito,</hi> that he would ſeem not to require that Honour which we ought to give him under a more publick appearance. God we know is preſent in all his Creatures, but yet we are not to Worſhip him as preſent in any of them; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, where he makes a ſenſible Manifeſtation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and appears by his <hi>Shechinah,</hi> or his Glory, as to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the burning Buſh, and to others in like manners: and it would be very ſtrange to make the Bread in the Euchariſt a <hi>Shechinah</hi> of God, which appears without any Alteration juſt as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was made ſuch; and eſpecially, to make it ſuch a continuing <hi>Shechinah</hi> as the Papiſts do, that Chriſt is preſent in it, not only in the action and ſolemn Celebration, but <hi>extra uſum,</hi> as they ſpeak, and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manenter,</hi> even after the whole Solemnity and Uſe is over; that he ſhould continue there, as a <hi>praeſens Numen,</hi> as <hi>Boileau</hi> expreſly calls it<note n="a" place="margin">de Euchoriſtiae Adorat. <hi>p. 140.</hi>
               </note>, and be ſhowed and carried about and honoured as ſuch, and dwell in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63797:10"/>the Species as long as they continue, as truly as he dwelt in the Fleſh, before that was crucified; this is ſtrange and monſtrous even to thoſe who think Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament, but not ſo as the Papiſts believe, nor ſo as to be worſhipped. I mean the <hi>Lutherans.</hi> But to bring the matter to cloſer iſſue; the Papiſts themſelves are forced to confeſs, that if the Bread remain after Conſecration, and be ſtill Bread, and be not Tranſubſtantiated into the Body of Chriſt, that they are then Idolaters. So <hi>Fiſher</hi> againſt <hi>Oecolampadius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. in expreſs words. So <hi>Coſter</hi> in his <hi>Enchiridion de Euch. c.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">In tali errore at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Idololatria, qualis in orbe terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nunquam vel viſus vel auditus fuit. Tolerabilior eſt enim error eorum qui pro Deo colunt Statuam auream aut argenteam, aut al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius materiae ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem, quomodo Gentiles Deos ſuos venerabantur, vel panum rubrum in haſtam elevatum quod narratur de Lappis, vel viva animalia ut quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Aegyptii, quam eorum qui fruſtum panis. <hi>Coſter Ench. c.</hi> 8. <hi>S.</hi> 10. Longe potiori ratione ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſandi eſſent infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles Idololatrae qui Statuas adoraverunt, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If the true Body of Chriſt be not preſent in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then they are left in ſuch an Error and Idolatry, as was never ſeen or heard; for that of the Heathens would be more tolerable, who Worſhip a golden or ſilver Statue for God, or any other Image, or even a red Cloth, as the</hi> Laplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>are ſaid to do, or living Animals, as the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>than of thoſe who worſhip a piece of Bread.</hi> And again, <hi>Thoſe Infidel Idolaters would be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, who worſhipt their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</hi> To whom I ſhall add <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Sacramentarii omnes negant Sacramentum Adorandum &amp; Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam appellant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi Adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; neque id mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum videri deber, cum ipſi non credant Chriſtum reipſa eſſe praeſentem, &amp; panem Euchariſtiae reipſa nihil eſſe niſi panem ex furno, <hi>Bellarm. de Euch.</hi> l. 4. c. 29.</note>, who ſaies, <hi>It does not ſeem ſtrange, that they call the Adoration of the Sacrament Idolatry, who do not believe that Chriſt is there truly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63797:11"/>preſent, but that the Bread is ſtill true Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the Bread do ſtill remain Bread in the Hoſt, and the Elements in the Euchariſt are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially changed into the natural and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Body and Blood of Chriſt, then it is confeſt Idolatry, and it is not ſtrange according to <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> that it ſhould be ſo; and then ſure it will be true <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Bread-worſhip too, if that be Bread which they Worſhip, and be not the natural Body of Chriſt; that which is <hi>there preſent,</hi> that they adore; and if <hi>that be only Bread,</hi> then they adore <hi>Bread.</hi> And here I ſhould enter that controverſie, which has given riſe to moſt of their abominable Abuſes and Errors about the Euchariſt; the making both a God of it, and alſo a true Sacrifice of this God inſtead of a Sacrament, which Chriſt intended it, and that is their Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; but a great man has ſpared me this trouble, by his late excellent Diſcourſe againſt it, to which I ſhall wholly refer this part of our preſent Controverſie, and ſhall take it for granted, as any one muſt, who reads that, that (unleſs in <hi>Boileau</hi>'s Phraſe<note n="a" place="margin">Homo opinioſus cui tenacit as Error is ſenſum communem abſtulit, <hi>Boil. p. 159.</hi>
               </note>, he be ſuch a Bigot, whoſe tenaciouſneſs of his Error, has quite bereaved him of common Senſe, which is an unlucky Character of his own Friends) that Doctrine is falſe; and therefore, that the charge of Idolatry in this matter, is by their own Confeſſion true. But there are ſome more cautious and wary men amongſt them, who out of very juſt and reaſonable Fears
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63797:11"/>and Suſpicions, that Tranſubſtantion ſhould not prove true, and that they may happen to be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in that, have thought of another way, to cover and excuſe their Idolatry; and that is, not from the <hi>Truth,</hi> but meerly from the <hi>Belief</hi> of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation. <hi>As long,</hi> ſay they, <hi>as we believe Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation to be true, and do really think that the Bread and Wine are converted into the ſubſtance of Chriſts Body and Blood, and ſo Worſhip the Sacrament upon that account, tho we ſhould be miſtaken in this our belief; yet as long as we think that Chriſt is there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and deſign only to Worſhip him, and not the Bread, which we believe to be done away; this were enough to free us from the charge of Idolatry.</hi> To which, becauſe it is the greateſt, and the beſt Plea they have, and they that make it have ſome miſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, I doubt not, that Tranſuſtantiation will not hold; I ſhall therefore give a full Anſwer to it, in the following Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All Idolatry does proceed from a miſtaken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and a falſe ſuppoſal of the mind, which being groſs and unreaſonable, will not at all excuſe thoſe who are guilty of it; there were never any Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but might plead the excuſe of a miſtake, and that not much more culpable and notorious, one would think, than the miſtake of thoſe who think a bit of Bread, or a Wafer, is turn'd by a few words into a God. They all thought, however blindly and fooliſhly, that whatever it was they worſhipt, ought to be worſhipt upon ſome account or other; that it was a true and fit Object, and that Adoration right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong'd to it. Idolatry, tho it be a great Sin, and a great injury and affront to God, yet ariſes not ſo much from the malice of the will, as the blindneſs and darkneſs of the underſtanding; there were hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63797:12"/>ever any ſuch Idolaters as maliciouſly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly intended to affront the true God, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping falſe Gods or Creatures; as if a Subject ſhould paſs by his Prince out of ill will, and a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to affront and defie him, and give the Reverence and Homage that was due to him, to a Rebel or fellow Subject ſtanding by him; but they did this, becauſe they miſtook the perſon, and thought this to be the Prince that was not, or that he was there where he was not, or that that which was there, ought to be worſhipt for his ſake; ſtill falſly ſuppoſing that they ought to worſhip that wrong Object, which they took to be right; or in that falſe manner which they took to be true; for if a miſtake will excuſe, it will excuſe in one as well as another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tho they do not only think and believe that which they worſhip, to be a true Divine Object; but it really be ſo in it ſelf, and that which they have in their Thoughts and intentions to worſhip, be right; yet they may ſtill be guilty of Idolatry; for ſo were the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Idolatry of the golden Calf, whereby they intended not to throw off the Worſhip of the true God, <hi>The God of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>who brought them out of the land of Egypt;</hi> for they appointed the Feaſt to him under that Title, and under the Name of <hi>Jehovah</hi> at the ſame time; and ſo in the Idolatry of the Calves ſet up by <hi>Jeroboam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>K.</hi> 12.27, 28.</note> they were not deſigned to draw off the people from wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the ſame God, who was worſhipt at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> but only to do it in another place, and after another manner; but ſtill as <hi>T. G.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cath. no Idol. <hi>p.</hi> 330.</note> ſays of the <hi>Roman</hi> Idolaters, ſo it may be ſaid of theſe <hi>Jewiſh,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63797:12"/>That <hi>what they had in their Minds and Intentions to Worſhip, was the true God; and whatever was the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial object of their Worſhip, he was the formal;</hi> for they did no more think the Gold, than the Papiſts think the Bread to be God. So the <hi>Manichees</hi> in their Idolatry, which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> often mentions<note n="b" place="margin">Contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Manicheum, <hi>l. 1. c. 3. Tom. 1.</hi> de Geneſi contra Manich. <hi>l. 2. c. 25. Tom. 2. Epiſt. 74.</hi> ad Deuterium, Solem etiam &amp; Lunam adorant &amp; colunt.</note>, of adoring the Sun and Moon, the Object which they had in their <hi>Minds,</hi> and <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>Purpoſes</hi> to Worſhip, was Chriſt, as much as the Papiſts have him in the Euchariſt. I would only ask, if a perſons having a right Object in his mind, in his thoughts and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to adore, which <hi>T. G.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Catholicks no Idolaters, <hi>p. 329, 330.</hi>
               </note> ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten pretends, would excuſe him from Idolatry; then ſuppoſe a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould before Conſecration, Worſhip the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Elements, to prevent which they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally keep them from being ſeen; yet in the Thoughts, and Intentions, and Purpoſes of his mind, deſign to worſhip Chriſt then ſuppoſed, tho falſly, to be there, as they Worſhip him afterwards; whether this would be Idolatry in him or no? If not, then they may worſhip the unconſecrated Elements, as well as conſecrated, even whilſt they believe they are Bread; if it be, then having a right Object in our Thoughts, and Purpoſes, and Intentions, will not excuſe from Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whatever was the material Object of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip, it was not worſhipt for it ſelf, no more than the Bread or its Accidents are by the Papiſts in the Euchariſt; but as they ſay of the Hoſt, becauſe they believed that the true Object of worſhip was really preſent in it, or in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63797:13"/>manner united to it<note n="a" place="margin">Deos relictis ſedibus propriis non recuſare nec fugere, habitaculainire ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena, quinimo jure dedicationis impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos ſimulachrorum coaleſcere inunctioni, <hi>Arnob. contra gent. l. 6.</hi>
               </note>; ſo did the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who thought the Gods themſelves, or at leaſt a Divine Power, was brought into their Images, by their Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that it reſided and dwelt there, and they worſhipped their Images only upon this account<note n="b" place="margin">Deos per ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachra Veneramur, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>. Now if they had thought this of the true God himſelf, that it was he, and not any falſe God that was thus preſent in their Images, this would have been nevertheleſs Idolatry. Thus the <hi>Manichees,</hi> who worſhipt the Sun, did not worſhip it for it ſelf, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they believed Chriſt had placed his Tabernacle in the Sun; ſo the more Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Idolaters among the Heathens,<note place="margin">See Voſſ. de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lol. <hi>l. 8. c. 1.</hi>
               </note> who worſhipt the ſeveral Things of Nature, as parts, they thought, of the Great and Omnipreſent God; they did not worſhip them pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for themſelves, but as God was in them, and they were as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Aut partes ejus aut mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ejus, aut aliquid jubſtantiae ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. l. 24. <hi>contra</hi> Fauſtum.</note>. Either parts of him, or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of him, or ſomething of his ſubſtance, as the Papiſts believe the Sacrament to be his Body. Thus they deified the things of Nature, tho they thought there was but one Supreme God, whom they worſhipt in them, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> ſays of them; they believe<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Euſeb. Praepar. Evangel.</hi> l. 3. c. 13.</note>. That <hi>one God fills all things with his various power, and pervades all things, and that he is to be worſhipped in, and by all viſible things;</hi> but yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63797:13"/>they denied that thoſe viſible things were to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt for themſelves, but for the ſake of God, and thoſe inviſible Powers of God, which were in them, as appears from the ſame place<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, <hi>They do not,</hi> they ſay, <hi>make Gods of the viſible Bodies of the Sun, Moon and Stars, or the other ſenſible parts of the World; but they worſhip thoſe inviſible Powers that are in them of that God, who is God over all.</hi> Nay the <hi>Egyptians</hi> themſelves, did not as <hi>Celſus</hi> pleads even for thoſe Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, worſhip their brute Animals, but only as they were <hi>Spmbols</hi> of <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Orig. contra Cel. <hi>l. 3.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet notwithſtanding this Plea of Idolaters, they may juſtly be charged with worſhipping thoſe material Objects, which they ſay, as the Papiſts, when we charge them with Breadworſhip, that they do not Worſhip. So the <hi>Egyptians</hi> might be charged with brute worſhip, the Heathens with the Worſhip of the Sun and Moon; and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.17.</note> expreſly Reproaches and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes the Idolaters with worſhipping a Stock or Stone, or a piece of Wood; tho it was the conſtant Plea and Pretence of the Heathens, that they did no more worſhip thoſe material Objects, than the Papiſts do Bread.<note n="e" place="margin">Non ego illum lapidem colo nec il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud ſimulachrum quod eſt ſine ſenſu, <hi>Aug. in Pſal. 69.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I do not Worſhip the ſenſeleſs Stone or Image, which has Eyes and ſees not, Ears and hears not,</hi> ſaies the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> and in <hi>Arnobius, We do not worſhip the Braſs, or the Gold, or Silver,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63797:14"/>or any of the matter of which our Images are made</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nos nequeaera, neque auri argenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que materias neque alias quibus ſigna conficiunt eas eſſe per ſe Religioſa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernimus numina, ſed eos in his colimus eoſque veneramur quos dedicatio infert Sacra <hi>Arnobius contra Gentes.</hi>
               </note>; and in St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> again, <hi>Do ye think we or our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſuch Fools as to take theſe for Gods</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque adeone Majores noſtros inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientes fuiſſe creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt ut Deos —</note>? No, they would diſown it as much as <hi>Boileau</hi> does, <hi>With his, who ſhall ſay we adore the Bread or Wine?</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Quis nos adorare panem &amp; vinum? <hi>Boileau,</hi> p. <hi>160.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>T. G</hi>'s. pretending <hi>that we run upon that falſe ground, that Catholicks believe the Bread to be God.</hi> And yet, I ſee not why there may not be good reaſon to charge the one, as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If thoſe other Idolaters had been ſo fooliſh and abſurd, as to believe and think, that thoſe things which they worſhipt were their very Gods them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſubſtantially preſent, and that the viſible ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their Idols, had been converted and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the ſubſtance of their Gods; this would have made their Idolatry only more horribly ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and ridiculous, but would not in the leaſt have made it more excuſable. If the <hi>Jews</hi> had thought that by the powerful words of Conſecration, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by <hi>Aaron</hi> their High Prieſt, the Calf had been turned into the very ſuſtance of God, and that, tho the Figure and Shape of the Calf had remained, and the Accidents and Species of Gold, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to their ſight; yet that the ſubſtance of it had been perfectly done away, and that only God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, had been there under thoſe appearing Species of a golden Calf; would this have mended the matter, or better excuſed their Idolatry, becauſe they had been ſo extremely ſottiſh, <hi>That they conceived the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63797:14"/>Gold not to be there at all, but in the place thereof, the only true and eternal God; and ſo, altho the Object (or rather Subject) materially preſent in ſuch a caſe would have been the golden Calf; yet their Act of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration would not have been terminated formally upon that, but only upon God,</hi> as <hi>T. G.</hi> ſaies of the Bread, <hi>p.</hi> 329. Or if the <hi>Manichees</hi> had thought the Body of the Sun had been converted into the glorious Body of Jeſus Chriſt, would this have ſignified any thing to bring them of; <hi>if their miſtake had been,</hi> as <hi>T. G.</hi> ſaies, <hi>p.</hi> 327. theirs is concerning the Bread, <hi>that they believed the Sun not to be there at all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what they would have in their minds would not, or could not be the Sun, but the only true and eternal Son of God.</hi> Indeed they had as it appears from St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eum (ſc. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum) navim quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam eſſe dicitis, eum triangulum eſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibetis, id eſt, per quandam trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulam caeli Fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram lucem iſtam mundo terriſque radiare. Auguſt. contra Fauſtum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaeum, <hi>l. 20. c. 6.</hi> Neſcio quam navim per foramen Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulum micantem at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que lucentem, quam confictam cogitatis, adoretis <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note>, ſome ſuch abſurd Imagination; they did think that it was not the material Sun, which appeared to their ſenſes; but a certain <hi>Navis,</hi> which was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſt, that <hi>did radiate,</hi> through the triangular <hi>Feneſtra</hi> in the Heavens to the World, and to the Earth. Theſe wretched Fig. ments of theirs, whereby they made the Father the Light, that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible, and placed Chriſt in the Sun and Moon, and the Holy Ghoſt in the Air<note n="b" place="margin">Trinitati loca tria datis; patri unum <hi>i. e.</hi> lumen in acceſſibile, filio duo Solem &amp; Lunam, ſpiritui ſancto rurſus unum, Aeris hunc omnem ambitum, <hi>Ibid. c. 7.</hi>
               </note>, and called theſe the <hi>Seals of their ſubſtance</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Sedes ejuſdem ſubſtantiae dicatis, <hi>Ibid. c. 8.</hi>
               </note>; theſe made them indeed as he ſays, worſhip on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Figments of their own cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy heads, and things that were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63797:15"/>not<note n="d" place="margin">In iis non quod ſunt, ſed quod vobis dementiſſime fingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis adoratis, <hi>Ib. c. 9.</hi> Vos autem colitis ea quae nec dii nec ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſunt. quoniam prorſus nulla ſunt, <hi>Ib. c. 9.</hi>
               </note>; but yet this madneſs and extravagance did not excuſe them from Idolatry, which he ſtill charges them withal. They worſhipt that in the Sun, which was not there, as the Papiſts do in the Sacrament, to wit, Chriſts natural Body, let it be Phantaſtick or not; and they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured <hi>to turn away the Senſes of men,</hi> as he ſays<note n="e" place="margin">Senſus Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium conantur aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, &amp; nonnullo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum avertunt. <hi>Id. Enarrat in Pſal. 10.</hi>
               </note>, from that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sun, and perſwade them that it was Chriſt himſelf. So that as <hi>T. G.</hi> ſays of their miſtake concerning the Bread, <hi>They did not in their minds, affirm the Sun to be, but not to be,</hi> p. 330. and ſo it could not according to him, be the <hi>Object of their worſhip, becauſe whatever is ſo, the underſtanding muſt affirm (either truly or falſly)</hi> to be, <hi>p.</hi> 329.</p>
            <p>There was an Idolatry among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which <hi>Xenophon</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyrop.</hi> l. 8.</note>, and <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Curtius</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3.</note> give an account of, in their worſhip of Fire, and carrying it about with the moſt ſtately Pomp and Solemnity upon ſilver Altars, and a great Train of Prieſts and others; which does the moſt reſemble the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying about the Hoſt in Proceſſion of any thing I have met with, as it is deſcribed by <hi>Curtius.</hi> Here the ſacred Fire as they call'd it, which no doubt was conſecrated by ſome Religious Ceremonies, and was no more counted <hi>ignis ex culinâ,</hi> than the holy Bread is <hi>panis ex furno;</hi> if they had ſuppoſed it by the magical Charms of the Prieſts to have been turned into ſome other ſubſtance than common Fire, and had thought it to have become the moſt noble Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of the great God, or the illuſtrious Veil, under
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63797:15"/>which lay the Divinity of the great Lord of the World, and that all the ſubſtance of common Fire was quite changed, and done away in this ſacred and eternal Fire, as they accounted it<note n="a" place="margin">Ignis quem ipſi ſacrum &amp; aeternum vocabant, argenetis altaribus perfereba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Curt. Ib.</hi>
               </note>, this would not ſure have made them to be no Idolaters. <hi>T. G.</hi> will make himſelf a very great Patron of dolaters, if with this Art and Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of his he can bring them off, as he would the Worſhippers of the Hoſt, by the meer adding of more thick Groſneſs, and more Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to their other miſtakes. He will have<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 322.</note> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to take the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf for God, and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> the Sun to be God, and perhaps ſome of the moſt ſtupid Heathens did take their very Images for Gods, and by his way, theſe were the moſt excuſable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the moſt miſtaken. Theſe miſtakes would after this rate do great and extraordinary things for Idolaters, and would be much better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, than her pretended Infallibility; and indeed 'tis theſe muſt bring off her, and her Members from the guilt, tho not from the Acts of Idolatry, as well as from other things, or elſe ſhe and they are in a very ſad and deſperate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>But now I dare appeal to any man, who ſhall take in all thoſe Conſiderations I have mentioned together, whether the Papiſt's adoring the Hoſt, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſuppoſal and belief of Tranſubſtantiation, if that be not true, will excuſe them from Idolatry, and whither if a miſtake in this Caſe, will excuſe them, it will not excuſe the groſſeſt Idolatry in the World? Notwitſtanding all the little Shifts and Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that <hi>T. G.</hi> uſes to wriggle himſelf out of this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63797:16"/>ſtreight and difficulty, into which his learned Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary had driven him.</p>
            <p>HAving conſidered the Adoration of the Hoſt, as it is Taught in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I ſhall now conſider the Practice of it, which is more plain and evident, and notorious to all the World; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they would palliate and diſguiſe their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. According to their Miſſal, which is wholly different in this, as well as other things from the old Lyturgic, and Euchariſtic forms, as I ſhall ſhow by and by, the Prieſt<note n="a" place="margin">Celebrans hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am inter pollices te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens — genuflexus eam adorat tum uſque in terram ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuflexus hoſtiam ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam veneratur — ſic de calice reponit calicem ſuper corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale &amp; genuflexus ſanguinem reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter adorat illum populo oſtendens ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum genuflexus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratur in Canon. Miſſ. genuflexus reverentiam facit Sacramento.</note> in every Maſs, as ſoon as he has conſecrated the Bread and Wine, <hi>with bended Knees, he adores the Sacrament</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſſale Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num c.</hi> 9. Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum genuflexus ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Capite inclinato verſus Sacramentum dicit Intelligibili vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce Agnus Dei qui tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis peccati mundi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere nobis, Da no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis pacem.</note>, <hi>that</hi> which he has conſecrated, <hi>that</hi> very thing which is before him, upon the Paten, and in the Chalice, and gives the ſame Worſhip and Subjection, both of Body and Mind to it, as he could to God or Chriſt himſelf; for with his Head, and his Soul, bowing towards it, and his Eyes and Thoughts fixt upon it, and directed to it, he prays to it, as to Chriſt himſelf: <hi>Lamb of God that takeſt away the Sins of the World, have Mercy upon us, Grant us Peace</hi> and the like; <hi>then the Prieſt riſing up after he has thus adored it himſelf, he lifts it up as high as conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently he can above his head, and with Eyes fixt upon it, he ſhows it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63797:16"/>to be devoutly adored by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Sacerdos poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ipſe hoſtiam genuflexus adoravit, continuo ſe erigens quantum commode poteſt, elevat in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; intentis in eam oculis populo reverenter oſtendit adorandam.</note>, who having notice alſo, by ringing the Maſs Bell, as ſoon as they ſee it, fall down in the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Adorations to it, as if it were the very appearance of God himſelf, and if Chriſt himſelf were viſibly preſent before them, they could not ſhow more acts of Reverence and Devotion, and Worſhip to him, than they do to the Hoſt; they Pray to it, and uſe the very Forms of Perition and Invocation to that, as to Chriſt himſelf; ſuch as theſe, <hi>O ſaving Hoſt, or bleſſed Sacrament which openeſt the door of Heaven, give me ſtrength and and power againſt dangers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all my Enemies</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">O ſalutaris Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia, quae caeli pandis oſtium bella pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt hoſtilia, Da robur, fer auxilium. Hymnus in Feſto corporis Chriſti in Brevia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </note>. <note n="e" place="margin">Adoro te devote latens Deitas, quae ſub his figuris vere latitas, tibi ſe cor meum ſubjicit, Deum meum te confiteor. Fac me tibi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis credere, in te ſpem habere, te de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere, praeſta menti de te vivere &amp; te illi ſemper dulce ſapere, <hi>Rythmus,</hi> St. <hi>Thom.</hi> ad Euchariſt in Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</note> 
               <hi>Make me always more to believe, to hope in thee, to love thee; Grant that my Soul may always live upon thee, and that thou mayſt always taſt ſweet unto it.</hi> Thus both the Prieſt, and the People are ſeveral times to Adore and Worſhip both the Hoſt and the Cup in the Celebration of the Euchariſt, and they will not diſown, nor cannot, their directing and terminating their Devotions and Prayers upon the Sacrament, which is before them; Prayers, they call them to the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt<note n="f" place="margin">Ad Sacram. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiam <hi>Rythmus Rom.</hi> breviar.</note>; and 'tis become a common form of Doxology amongſt them, inſtead of ſaying, Praiſe be given to God, to ſay, Praiſe be given to the moſt holy Sacrament<note n="g" place="margin">Laus ſacratiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Sacramento.</note>; as 'tis in one of their Authors, inſtead
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63797:17"/>of ye ſhall pray to God, ye ſhall pray to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="h" place="margin">Orlandinus hiſt.</note>. <hi>Sanders</hi> in his Book of the Supper of the Lord<note n="i" place="margin">Corpori &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guini Chriſti ſub Speciebus panis &amp; vini omnis honor, Laus &amp; Gratiarum actio in ſecula ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum. Sanderus de caena Dom.</note>, inſtead of Glory be to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, turns it thus, To the Body and Blood of our Saviour, under the Species of Bread and Wine, be all Honour and Praiſe, and Thankſgiving for evermore, as if it were another Perſon of the bleſſed God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
            <p>This Adoration is not only in the time of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when it is properly the Lords Supper and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; but at other times out of it, whenever it is ſet upon the Altar with the Candles burning, and the Incenſe ſmoking before it, or hung up in its rich Shrine and Tabernacle, with a Canopy of State over it. And not only in the Church which is ſanctified, they ſay, by this Sacrament, as by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God himſelf<note n="k" place="margin">Bellarm. de ſanct. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note>, but when it is carried through the Sreets in a ſolemn and pompous Proceſſion, as it is before the Pope, when he goes abroad, juſt as the <hi>Perſian</hi> fire was before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Curt.</hi> l. 3. <hi>S.</hi> 3.</note>, meerly by way of ſtate, or for a ſuperſtitious end, that he may better the be Guarded and Defended by the company of his God<note n="m" place="margin">Ad capitis illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſacri cuſtodiam praeſidialem &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronalem. <hi>Perron. de Euch.</hi> l. 3. c. 19.</note>. In all theſe times it is to worſhipped and adcred by all perſons as it paſſeth by, as if it were the Glory of God which paſſed by. <hi>They are</hi> like Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>to make haſt and bow their heads to the Earth and worſhip</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.8.</note>; but above
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63797:17"/>all, upon that high day, which they have dedicated to this Sacrament, as if it were ſome new Deity, the <hi>Feſtum Dei,</hi> as they call it, the Feaſt of God, or the <hi>Feſtum Corporis Chriſti,</hi> the Feaſt of the Body of Chriſt; for to call the Sacrament God, is a general Expreſſion among them, as when they have received the Sacrament, to ſay, <hi>I have received my Maker to day;</hi> and the Perſon who in great Churches, is to carry the Sacrament to the numerous Communicants, is called, <hi>Bajulus Dei,</hi> the Porter or Carrier of God; and they always account it, and ſo always reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence it, as <hi>Boileau</hi> falſly ſays<note n="o" place="margin">Euchariſtiam pro praeſente numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſemper habuiſſe Verteres.</note>, the Ancients did, as a <hi>preſent Numen and Deity.</hi> This Feaſt was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> about the middle of the twelfth Century; and again by <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth in the beginning of the <hi>13th,</hi> as is owned by themſelves, upon the occaſion of a Viſion to one <hi>Juliana,</hi> who ſaw a crack in the Moon, that ſignified, it ſeems, a great defect in the Church for want of this Solemnity: ſuch was the riſe of this great Feſtival<note n="p" place="margin">Bzovii Annal. in Contin. <hi>Baron. Anno Dom.</hi> 1230.</note>, and ſo late was its Inſtitution in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, in which alone, and in no other Chriſtian Church of the World, it is obſerved to this day. And that the whole practice of the Adoration to the Hoſt is Novel, and unknown to the primitive Church, and to the Ancient Writers, I ſhall endeavour to make evident a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that bold and impudent Canon of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which is the firſt Council that commanded it in theſe words<note n="q" place="margin">Si quis dixerit, non eſſe hoc Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum peculiari fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivia celebritate ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandum, neque in proceſſionibus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum laudabilem &amp; Univerſalem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſanctae ritum &amp; conſuetudinem, ſolenniter circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtandum, vel non publice ut adoretur, populo proponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ejus Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores eſſe Idololatras anathema ſit. Concil. Trident. <hi>Can.</hi> 6. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 13.</note>, <hi>If any one ſhall ſay that the Sacrament is not to be worſhipt by a peculiar Feſtival, nor to be ſolemnly carried
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63797:18"/>about in Proceſſions according to the laudable and univerſal manner and cuſtom of the Holy Church, nor to be publickly propoſed to the People, that it may be adored by them, and that the Worſhippers of it are Idolaters; let him be accurſed.</hi> To confront this inſolent pretence of theirs, that it was an univerſal cuſtom of the Church, thus to carry the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Proceſſions, the ingenuous confeſſion of their own <hi>Caſſander</hi> is ſufficient, <hi>The cuſtom,</hi> ſays he<note n="r" place="margin">Conſuetudo qua panis Euchariſtiae in publica pompa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuus circumfertur ac paſſim omnium oculis ingeritur, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter veterum morem ac mentem haud ita longo tempore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducta &amp; recepta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur. Illi enim hoc myſterium in tanta religione ac venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione habuerunt, ut non modo ad ejus perceptionem, ſed ne inſpectionem qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem admitterent, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi fideles, quos Chriſti membra &amp; tanta participatione dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos eſſe exiſtimarent, quare ante Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Catechumeni Energumeni, paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, denique non Communicantes Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconi voce &amp; Oſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ariorum Miniſterio ſecludebantur, <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> Conſult.</note>, <hi>of carrying about the Sacramental Bread in publick pomp, to be ſeen and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to all eyes, is contrary to the mind and cuſtom of the Ancients, and ſeems to be lately brought in and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; for they had this myſtery in ſuch religious Veneration, that they would not admit any, not only to the partaking, but not to the ſight of it, but the Faithful, whom they accounted members of Chriſt, and worthy to partake of ſuch a Myſtery. Wherefore all thoſe who were but Catechumens, or were Energumeni or Penitents, and not Communicants, were always put out and diſmiſt at the Celebration of it.</hi> Whether they be Idolaters for adoring the Sacrament, I have conſidered already, and their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice joined with their Doctrine, makes it more evident. I ſhall now prove that this Adoration of theirs,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63797:18"/>was neither commanded nor uſed by Chriſt, or the Apoſtles, nor by the Primitive Church, nor is truly meant and deſigned by any of thoſe Authorities of the Fathers, which they produce for it; and upon a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral view of the whole matter, That it is a very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and ridiculous thing that tends moſt ſhamefully to reproach, and expoſe Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it was not uſed or commanded by Chriſt or the Apoſtles, is plain from the account that all the Evangeliſts give us of Chriſts celebrating this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with his Apoſtles, where is only mention of their taking and eating the Bread, and drinking the Wine, after it was bleſſed by him, but not the leaſt tittle of their adoring it; ſo far from it, that they were not then in a poſture of Adoration, which they ſhould have been in, if they had inwardly adored it, which makes this not only a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Argument, as <hi>Boileau</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Adorat. Euch.</hi> l. 2. c. 1.</note> would have it, but a poſitive one. To take off this argument from the no mention of any ſuch command or practice of Adoration to the Sacrament in the Goſpel; he ſays, Neither is the Adoration of Chriſt, preſcribed in expreſs words<note n="t" place="margin">Nullo exiis loco conceptis verbis praeſcriptam fuiſſe Adorationem, (ſc, Chriſti) <hi>p.</hi> 27.</note>, nor that of the Holy Ghoſt, either commanded or performed<note n="u" place="margin">Nullibi praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ejus Adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aut confeſtim peractam conceptis intelligamus, <hi>p.</hi> 98.</note>. But I hope all thoſe places of Scripture, that ſo fully tell us, that both Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt are God, do ſufficiently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us to worſhip them, by bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us worſhip God; and if it and told us that the Sacrament is as much God as they, it had then commanded us to adore it. There are ſufficient inſtances of Chriſts being adored, when he appeared upon Earth, and had the other Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63797:19"/>aſſumed a bodily Shape; thoſe who had ſeen and known it, would have particularly adored it, and ſo would the Apoſtles, no doubt, have done the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, if they had thought that, when it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, an object of worſhip. St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi> c.</note> when he wrote to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> of their very great Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence in receiving the Lords Supper, had very good occaſion to have put them in mind of adoring it, had that been their Duty; this then would have been a proper means to have brought them to the higheſt reverence of it; but he never intimates any thing of worſhipping it, when he delivers to them, the full account of its inſtitution, and its deſign; nor never reproves them among all their other unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy abuſes of it, for their not adoring it; and 'tis a very ſtrange fetch in <hi>Boileau</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>103.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>, that he would draw St. <hi>Pauls</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of examining our ſelves before we eat, to mean our adoring when, or what we eat; and that not diſcerning the Lords body, and being guilty of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, is the not worſhipping the Sacrament, which he never ſo much as touches upon among all their other faults. Are there not many other ways of abuſing the Sacrament, beſides the not worſhipping it? this is like his firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtles<note n="x" place="margin">l. 1. c. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ep. ad Smyr.</hi> at ipſemet nos docet nihil nos diligere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere praeter So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Deum.</note>, that becauſe he ſays, the Sacrament ought to be loved, therefore he meant that it ought to be adored. At which rate I ſhould be afraid to love this Gentleman however taking he was, leſt I ſhould conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him, or becauſe I am not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe him, therefore it would follow, that I muſt worſhip him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63797:19"/>
2. This Adoration was not in uſe in the Primitive Church, as I ſhall ſhow,
<list>
                  <item>1. From thoſe Writers who give us an account of the manner of celebrating the Euchariſt among the Ancient Chriſtians.</item>
                  <item>2. From the oldeſt Liturgies and Euchariſtick forms.</item>
                  <item>3. From ſome very antient Cuſtoms.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe moſt ancient Writers,<note place="margin">1. Juſtin Marty. 2. <hi>Apolog. verſus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Apoſtol. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</hi> l. 8. c. 11, 12, 13, 14. 3. Cyril Hieroſol. <hi>Catecheſ. myſtagog</hi> c 5.</note> 1. <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi> 2. The Author of the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions: And 3. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with the manner how they celebrated the Euchariſt, which was generally then one conſtant part of their publick worſhip; they give no account of any Adoration given to the Sacrament, or to the conſecrated Elements, tho they are very particular and exact in mentioning other leſs conſiderable things that were then in uſe, the Kiſs of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in token of their mutual Love and Reconcilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; this <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> mentions as the firſt thing juſt before the Sacrament<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>Apol. 2.</hi>
               </note>. In St. <hi>Cyril</hi>'s time<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Catech. myſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog.</hi> 5. <hi>Apoſtol. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> l. 8. c. 11.</note>, the firſt thing was the bringing of Water by the Deacon, and the Prieſts waſhing their hands in it, to denote that purity with which they were to compaſs Gods Altar; and then the Deacon ſpoke to the people, to give the holy Kiſs; then Bread was brought to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Prieſt, and<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſt. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</note> Wine mixt with Water in thoſe hot Countries,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63797:20"/>and after Prayers and Thankſgivings by the Prieſt, to which the people to joyned their <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Juſt. Martyr, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> The Deacons gave every one preſent, of the bleſſed Bread, and Wine, and Water; and to thoſe that were not preſent, they carried it home; this, ſays <hi>Juſtin Martyr, we account not common Bread, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Drink, but the Body and Blood of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note>, <hi>the bleſſed Food, by which our Fleſh and Blood is nouriſht, that is, being turned into it,</hi> which could not be ſaid of Chriſts natural Body; nor is there the leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any worſhip given to that, as there preſent, or to any of the bleſſed Elements. The others are longer and much later, and ſpeak of the particular Prayers and Thankſgivings that were then uſed by the Church, of the <hi>Surſum Corda,</hi> lift up your heart; which St.<note n="d" place="margin">Cyril Hieroſol. myſtagog. Cat. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaies, followed after the Kiſs of Charity; of the <hi>Sancta Sanctis,</hi> things holy belong to thoſe that are holy; then they deſcribe how they came to Communicate, how they held their hand<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ib.</note> when they received the Elements; how careful they were that none of them ſhould fall upon the Ground; but among all theſe moſt minute and particular Deſcriptions of their way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of receiving the Sacrament, no account is there of their adoring it, which ſurely there would have been, had there been any ſuch in the Primitive Church, as now is in the <hi>Roman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63797:20"/>
We own indeed, as <hi>Boileau</hi> objects to us<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>P.</hi> 106.</note>, that from theſe it appears, that ſome things were then in uſe, which we obſerve not now; neither do the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> all of them, for they are not eſſential, but indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent matters, as mixing Water with Wine, the Prieſt's waſhing, the Kiſs of Charity, and ſending the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to the abſent; but the Church may alter theſe upon good reaſons according to its prudence and diſcretion; but Adoration to the Sacrament, if it be ever a Duty, is always ſo, and never ought upon any account to be omitted; nor would have been ſo by the Primitive Chriſtians, had they had the ſame Opinion of it, that the Papiſts have now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the oldeſt Lyturgies, and the Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Forms; in them it appears that there was no ſuch Adoration to the Sacrament, till of late; for in none of them is there any ſuch mention, either by the Prieſt or the People, as in the <hi>Roman</hi> Miſſal and Ritual, nor any ſuch Forms of Prayer to it, as in their Breviary. <hi>Caſſander</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Caſſandri Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgic.</note> has collected together moſt of the old Liturgies, and Endeavours, as far as he can, to ſhew their agreement; with that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; but neither in the old <hi>Greek,</hi> nor in the old <hi>Latin</hi> ones, is there any inſtance to be produced of the Prieſts or the Peoples adoring the Sacrament, as ſoon as he had conſecrated it; but this was perfectly added, and brought in a-new into the <hi>Roman</hi> Lyturgy, after the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht in that Church, which has altered not only their Lyturgy, but even their Religion in good part, and made a new ſort of Worſhip unknown, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the firſt and beſt times of the Church, but for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63797:21"/>above a thouſand years after Chriſt; <hi>Boileau</hi> finding this, tho a negative Argument, preſs very hard upon them; and ſure it cannot but ſatisfie any reaſonable man, that there is no Direction in the ancient Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies for adoring the Sacrament; and it is very hard to require us to produce a Rubrick againſt it, when no body thought of that which after. Superſtition brought in; He would fain therefore find ſomething in an old Liturgy that ſhould look like that of their own; and no doubt but he might have eaſily met with abundant places for their worſhipping and adoring God and Chriſt at that ſolemn Office of the Chriſtian worſhip, the bleſſed Sacrament; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of the Liturgy called St. <hi>Chryſoſtomes,</hi> which he owns to be two hundred years later then St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> he produces a place<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boil.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>74.</hi> ex Chryſoſt. Liturg. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, wherein it is ſaid, That <hi>the Prieſt and the Deacon worſhip in the place they are in, and likewiſe the people;</hi> but do they worſhip the Sacrament? Is that, or only God and Chriſt the object of their worſhip there? Is there any ſuch thing to determine this as they have taken care there ſhould be in their Miſſal? where it is expreſly ſeveral times, they ſhall worſhip the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="i" place="margin">Sacramentum Adorare, <hi>Rom. miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> Cooperto calice Sacramentum ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, &amp; genuflexus Sacramentum ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare.</note>; but here in St. <hi>Chryſoſ.</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, 'tis God, who is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt, <hi>God be merciful to me a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chryſ. Lyturg.</note>; but in the <hi>Roman,</hi> 'tis the <hi>Sacrament is prayed to</hi>
               <note n="l" place="bottom">Stans oculis ad Sacramentum intentis precari.</note>, and they would reckon and account it as true Irreligion, not to worſhip and pray
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63797:21"/>to that, as not to worſhip God and Chriſt. So in the Lyturgy, that goes under the name of St. <hi>James,</hi> the Worſhip is only <hi>before</hi> the Holy Table<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lyturg. St. <hi>Jacobi.</hi>
               </note>, as it is in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and I hope <hi>Boileau</hi> will not pretend that this is <hi>to</hi> the Holy Table it ſelf. If whatever we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before, is the very Object of our Worſhip, then the Prieſt is ſo, as well as the Table; but it is neither he, nor the Table, nor the Sacrament, but only Chriſt himſelf, to whom this Worſhip is, or ought to be given at the Celebration of the Euchariſt; and therefore this Adoration was as well <hi>before</hi> as after the Conſecration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Elements, and ſo could not be ſuppoſed to be given to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There were ſeveral very ancient Cuſtoms rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Sacrament, which are no ways conſiſtent with the Opinion the Papiſts have of it now, and with the worſhip of it as a God. It was very old, and very uſual for Chriſtians to reſerve and keep by them, ſome of the Elements; the Bread eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, which they had received at the Sacrament, as is evident from <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Orat.</hi> c. 14. Accepto corpore Domini &amp; reſervato.</note>, and from St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">De Lapſis.</note>, who reports a very ſtrange think that happened to a Woman, and alſo to a Man, who had unduly gone to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and brought ſome part of it home with them. I ſhall not enquire whither this Cuſtom had not ſomething of Superſtition in it; whither in thoſe times of Danger and Perſecution, it were not of uſe; but had the Church then thought of it, as the Papiſts do now, they would not have ſuffered pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians to have done this; nay they would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63797:22"/>not have ſuffered them hardly to have toucht and handled, that which they had believed to be a God, no more than the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will now, which is ſo far from allowing this private Reſervation of the Elements, that out of profound Veneration, as they pretend to them, they wholly deny one part of them, the Cup to the Laity, and the other part, the Bread they will not, as the primitive Church, put into their hands, but the Prieſt muſt inject it into their Mouths.</p>
            <p>The ſending the Euchariſt not only to the Sick and Infirm, and to the Penitents, who were this way to be admitted to the Communion of the Church, <hi>in articulo mortis,</hi> as is plain from the known Story of <hi>Serapion</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> l. 6. c. 34.</note>; but the Biſhops of ſeveral Churches ſending it to one another, as a token and pledg of their Communion with each other; and<note n="q" place="margin">Iren. <hi>apud</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> it being ſent alſo to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians, who lived remote in the Country and private Places, which cuſtom was aboliſht by the Council of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea;</hi> theſe all ſhow, that tho the Chriſtians always thought the Sacrament a Symbol of Love, and Friendſhip, and Communion with the Church, ſo that by partaking of this one Bread they were all made as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>One Bread, and one Body;</hi> yet they could not think this to be a God, or the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natural Body of their Saviour, which they ſent thus commonly up and down, without that Pomp and Solemnity, that is now uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and without which I own it is not fit a Deity ſhould be treated. But above all, what can they think of thoſe, who anciently uſed to burn the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63797:22"/>Elements that remained after the Communion, as <hi>Heſychius</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.32.</note> teſtifies, was the cuſtom of the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> of burning what remain'd of the Fleſh of the Sacrifice, that was not eaten; but however this was done out of ſome reſpect, that what was thus ſacred might not otherwiſe be proſaned; yet they could not ſure account that to be a God, or to be the very natural and ſubſtantial Body of Chriſt, which they thus burnt and threw into the Fire.</p>
            <p>So great an honour and regard had the Primitive Church for the Sacrament, that as they accounted it the higheſt Myſtery and Solemneſt part of their Worſhip, ſo they would not admit any of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, who had been guilty of any great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Sin, nor the Catechumens, nor the Poſſeſt, and Energumeni, ſo much as to the ſight of it; the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Participation of this Myſtery, uſed always in thoſe times to go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>Caſſander</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Conſult. de Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumgeſt. Sacram.</note> owns, and <hi>Albaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinaeus</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">L'ancienne Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice de l'Egliſe ſur l'adminiſtration de l'Euchariſtie. liure prem. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15, 16, 17.</note> proves in his Book of the Euchariſt. And therefore, as it is plainly contrary to the Primitive practice, to carry the Sacrament up and down, and expoſe it to the Eyes of all Perſons; ſo the reaſon of doing it, that it may be worſhipt by all, and that thoſe, who do not partake of it, may yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore it; was, it is plain, never thought of in the primitive Church; for then they would have ſeen and worſhipped it, tho they had not thought ſit that they ſhould have partaken of it. But he that will ſee how widely the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> diflers from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63797:23"/>ancient Church in this, and other matters relating to the Euchariſt, let him read the learned <hi>Dallee</hi> his two Books of the Object of religious Worſhip.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now give an Anſwer to the Authorities which they produce out of the Fathers, and which Monſieur <hi>Boileau</hi> has, be tells us, been a whole year a gleaning out of them<note n="v" place="margin">Annuae vellicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis litirariae ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinium reddo. <hi>Praef. ad Lect.</hi> Boileau <hi>de Adorat. Euchar.</hi>
               </note>, if he has not rather pickt from the Sheaves of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Perrone.</hi> But all their Evidences out of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, as they are produced by him, and bound up together in one Bundle in his Book, I ſhall Examine and Anſwer too, I doubt not, in a much leſs time. They are the only Argument he pretends to for this Adoration; and when Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and all other Reaſons fail them, as they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally do, then they fly to the Fathers; as thoſe who are ſenſible their forces are too weak to keep the open Field, fly to the Woods, or the Mountains, where they know but very few can follow them. I take it to be ſufficient, that in any neceſſary Article of Faith, or Eſſential part of Chriſtian Worſhip, (which this of the Sacrament muſt be, if it be any part at all,) it is ſufficient that we have the Scripture for us, or that the Scripture is ſilent, and ſpeaks of no more than what we own and admit. In other external and indifferent Matters relating meerly to the Circumſtances of Worſhip, the Church may for outward Order and Decency, appoint what the Scripture does not. But as to what we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and what we are to Worſhip the moſt poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Argument from any humane Authority is of no weight, where there is but a Negative from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But we have ſuch a due regard to Antiquity, and are ſo well aſſured of our cauſe, were it to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63797:23"/>be tryed only by that, and not by Scripture, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> generally demurs to; that we ſhall not fear to allow them to bring all the Fathers they can for their Witneſſes in this matter, and we ſhall not in the leaſt decline their Teſtimony. <hi>Boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leau</hi> Muſters up a great many, ſome of which are wholly impertinent and inſigniſicant to the matter in hand, and none of them ſpeak home to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs he brings them for. He was to prove, that they Taught that the Sacrament was to be adored, as it is in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but they only Teach as we do, <hi>That it is to be had in great reverence</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, as all other things relating to the Divine Worſhip; <hi>that it is to be received with great Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both of Body and Soul,</hi> and in ſuch a Poſture, as is to expreſs this, <hi>A Poſture of Adoration; that Chriſt is then to be worſhipped</hi> by us in this Office eſpecially, as well as he is in all other Offices of our Religion; <hi>that his Body, and his Fleſh,</hi> which is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Divinity, and which he offered up to his Father as a Sacrifice for all Mankind, and by which we are Redeemed, and which we do ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally partake of in the Sacrament, that this is to be adored by us; but not as being corporally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent there, or that the Sacrament is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt with that, or for the ſake of that, or that which the Prieſt holds up in his Hands, or lyes upon the Altar, is to be the Object of our Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but only Chriſt and his bleſſed Body, which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>To theſe four Heads, I ſhall reduce the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which <hi>Boileau</hi> produces for the Adoration of the Hoſt, and which ſeem to ſpeak any thing to his purpoſe; and no wonder that among ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63797:24"/>Perſons that ſpeak as great things as can be of the Sacrament, and uſed, and perſwaded the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Devotion, as is certainly our Duty, in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it; there ſhould be ſomething that may ſeem to look that way to thoſe, who are very willing it ſhould, or that may by a little ſtretching be drawn further than their true and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine meaning, which was not to Worſhip the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament it ſelf, or the conſecrated Elements, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To Worſhip Chriſt,</hi> who is to be adored by us in all places, and at all times, but eſpecially in the places ſet apart for his Worſhip, and at thoſe times we are performing them in the Church, and upon the Altar, <hi>in Myſteriis,</hi> as St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſpeaks,<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Spir. St.</hi> l. 3. c. 12.</note> in the Myſteries, both of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, and in all the Offices of Chriſtian Worſhip,<note n="x" place="margin">Orat. <hi>II.</hi> de <hi>Gorgon.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> y ſaid of his Siſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> that She called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, who is honoured upon the the Altar. That Chriſt is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured upon the Altar, where we ſee the great and honourable work of mens Redemption as 'twas per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by his Death, repreſented to us, is not at all ſtrange; if it had been another, and more full word, that he <hi>was to be worſhipt there,</hi> 'tis no more than what is very allowable, tho it had not been in a Rhetorical Oration; 'tis no more than to ſay, <hi>That the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>was worſhipt upon the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Altar, or upon this Mountain.</hi> For 'tis plain, She did not mean to worſhip the Sacrament, as if that were Chriſt or God, for She made an ointment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63797:24"/>of it, and mixt it with her tears, and anointed her Body with it, as a Medicine to recover her Health, which ſhe did miraculouſly upon it. Now, ſure 'tis a very ſtrange thing that ſhe ſhould uſe that as a <hi>Plaiſter,</hi> which She thought to be a God; but She ſtill took it for Bread and Wine, that had extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Vertue in it, and it is ſo called there by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> the Antitypes<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note> of Chriſts Body and Blood, which ſhews they were not thought to be the ſubſtance of it; and ſhe had all theſe about her, and in her own keeping, as many private Chriſtians had in thoſe times; and there was no Hoſt then upon the Altar, when ſhe worſhipped Chriſt upon it, for it was in the night<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note>, ſhe went thus to the Church. So St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Bo leau, <hi>c. 7. l. 1.</hi> ex Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt.</note> in all the places quoted out of him, only recommends the worſhipping of Chriſt our bleſſed Saviour, and our coming to the Sacrament with all Humility and Reverence, like humble Supplicants upon our Knees, and with Tears in our Eyes, and all Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Sorrow for our Sins, and Love, and Honour to our Saviour, whom we are to meet there, and whom we do, as it were,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> Ep. Cor. <hi>10. c.</hi>
               </note> ſee upon upon the Altar, which is the great ſtreſs of all that is produced out of him. That <hi>we do not truly ſee him upon the Altar,</hi> the Papiſts muſt own, tho they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him there; but not ſo as to be viſible to our Senſes; and he is no more to be truly adored as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally preſent, than he is viſibly preſent. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">In Sermone 56 <hi>Stephanus</hi> in terris poſitus Chriſtum tangit in caelo.</note> ſays of St.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63797:25"/>
               <hi>Stephen,</hi> that <hi>he being on Earth, toucheth Chriſt in Heaven;</hi> juſt as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, <hi>Thou ſeeſt him on the Altar;</hi> and as he and any one that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſtrain an eaſie figurative Expreſſion, muſt mean, not by a bodily touch, or ſight, but by Faith<note n="d" place="margin">Non corporali tactu, ſed ſide.</note>, and by that we own, that we ſee Chriſt there, and that he is there preſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Adoring the Fleſh and Body of Chriſt,</hi> which tho conſidered without his Divinity, it would be worſhipping a Creature as St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſays<note n="e" place="margin">In actis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Epheſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, yet as it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways united to his Divinity, 'tis a true object of Worſhip, and ought to be ſo to us, who are to expect Salvation by it,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. Homil. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> even from the Blood, and the Body, and Fleſh of Chriſt; and therefore, as we inwardly truſt in it, ſo we ought to adore it, as no doubt the Angels do in Heaven, and as we are to do in all the Offices of our Religion; tho that be in Heaven, yet we are to worſhip it upon Earth, and eſpecially, when it is brought to our minds and thought, by that which is appointed by Chriſt himſelf to be the Figure and Memorial of it, the bleſſed Sacrament, there and in Baptiſm eſpecially, when we put on Chriſt, and have his Death, and Riſing again repreſented to us, and have ſuch great benefits of his Death and Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation beſtowed upon us; in theſe Myſteries we are, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Caro Chriſti, quam hodie in My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriis adoramus, <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> l. 3. <hi>de Sp. San.</hi> c. 12. <hi>apud Boil.</hi> p. 32.</note> ſays, to Adore the Body and the Fleſh of Chriſt, to which we imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and particularly owe them,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63797:25"/>and which we may truly call our Saviour. St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Auguſt. Enar. in <hi>Pſ. 98.</hi>
               </note> his Scholar after him, ſuppoſing that there was a great difficulty in that paſſage of the <hi>Pſalms, worſhip his footſtool,</hi> for ſo it is in the <hi>Latin</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Adorate ſcabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pedum ejus.</note>, without the Prepoſition <hi>at</hi> his footſtool, they laboured to reconcile this with that command of Worſhipping and Serving God alone; and to give an account how the Earth, which was Gods footſtool, could be worſhipt; and the way they take, was this, to make Chriſts Fleſh, which he took of the Earth, to be meant by that Earth which was Gods footſtool<note n="k" place="margin">Invenio quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſine Impieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te adoretur terra, ſcabellum pedum ejus; ſuſcepit enim de terra terram, quia caro de terra eſt, &amp; de carne Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae carnem accepit, <hi>Auguſt. Ib.</hi>
               </note>; and this, ſay they, we ought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; his Apoſtles did ſo whilſt he was upon Earth, and we do ſo now, whilſt he is in Heaven. We wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Fleſh of Chriſt, which was crucified for us, and by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of which we hope for Pardon and Salvation, we worſhip that, tho it be now in Heaven; we worſhip it in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Offices of our Religion<note n="l" place="margin">Ipſam carnem nobis manducan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ad ſalutem dedit (nemo autem illam carnem man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat, niſi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us adoraverit) <hi>Aug. Ib.</hi>
               </note>, that Fleſh which he gave to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by us for our Salvation, that we worſhip, <hi>for none eates that Fleſh, but he firſt worſhips:</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips that, if they pleaſe; tho St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> do not expreſly ſay that; but we will own, and we will be always ready to Worſhip the Fleſh of Chriſt, by which we are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and we will do this eſpecially at the Sacrament; and that more truly and properly, than they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will own, that we eat and manducate it, as St.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63797:26"/>
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, not with our Teeth, as we do the Bread, but eat it, and worſhip it too, as it is Heaven. St. <hi>Hierome</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel.</hi> Ibant Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni <hi>Hieroſolymam</hi> ut Chriſtum in illis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorarent locis, in quibus primum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelium de pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulo coruſcaverat.</note> ſays of ſome devout Chriſtians, <hi>That they went to</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>that they might adore Chriſt in thoſe places, where the Goſpel firſt ſhone from the Croſs.</hi> They went, that they might adore Chriſt in thoſe places; not that they believed him to be corporally preſent in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; much leſs, that they worſhipt the places them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but they made a more lively impreſſion of Chriſt upon them, and made them remember him with more Paſſion and Devotion; and ſo does the bleſſed Sacrament upon us, and we therefore worſhip Chriſt, whom we believe to be in Heaven in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as they worſhipt him in thoſe places, where they were eſpecially put in mind of him. Thus St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſays, <hi>He worſhipped Chriſt in the Grave,</hi> and that <hi>Paula worſhipped him in the Stall</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ad Paul. &amp; Euſtoch.</note>, and ſo we may be ſaid to worſhip him on the Croſs, or on the Altar, or in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet not to worſhip the Croſs, or the Altar, or the Sacrament it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Other places out of the Fathers brought by him for the Adoration of the Hoſt, mean only, that the Sacrament is to be had in great reverence and eſteem by us, as all things ſacred and ſet apart to religious uſes are; <hi>that a ſngular Veneration is due to the Euchariſt,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays<note n="o" place="margin">Euchariſtiae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri ſingularem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationem, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118 <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>, and as is to Baptiſm alſo, of which he uſes the ſame word, <hi>We venerate Baptiſm</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Baptiſmum, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicunque eſt, veneramur. <hi>Id Epiſt.</hi> 146.</note>, as we ought to do all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63797:26"/>the Rites and Ordinances of our Religion; this is meant by <hi>Origen</hi> in that firſt place of him produced by <hi>Boileau</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Euch. Ador. p.</hi> 10. <hi>ex Orig. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 13. Noſtis qui Divinis myſteriis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe conſueſtis, quomodo cum ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitis corpus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, cum omni cautela &amp; venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſervatis, ne ex eo parum quid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidat, ne conſecrati muneris aliquid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labatur. Reos enim vos creditis &amp; recte creditis, ſiquid inde per negligentiam decidat.</note> 
               <hi>Ye that are wont to be preſent at the Divine Myſteries, know how, when ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Body of Chriſt, ye keep it with all Caution and Veneration, that no part of the conſecrated gift be let fall; for ye think, and that rightly, that ye ſhould be guilty of a fault, if any of it ſhould be let fall through your negligence.</hi> And Chriſtans have this Care and Veneration of thoſe conſecrated Symbols of the Body and Blood of their Saviour, of theſe wonderful Pledges of his Love, that they would not willingly ſpill them, or let them fall to the ground, through their careleſneſs and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; they that have that due regard to the Holy Bible which they ought, would not trample it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their feet, or ſhow any ſuch diſreſpect to it; it was this, which <hi>Origen</hi> was recommending in that place from that example of their care and reſpect to the Sacrament Elements, that they ſhould give it alſo to the Word of God<note n="r" place="margin">Quod ſi cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca corpus ejus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta utimini cantela, &amp; merito urimini; quomodo putatis minoris eſſe piaculi Verbum Dei neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexiſſe quam Corpus ejus. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>But if ye uſe ſuch care, and that very deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly about keeping his Body, how do ye think it to be a leſs fault to neglect the word of God, than to neglect his Body.</hi> The Compariſon here made between the Word of God, and the Sacrament, ſo plainly ſhows that he no way meant its Adoration, that I wonder this Perſon was not aſhamed to pretend juſt before it,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63797:27"/>that he<note n="ſ" place="margin">Alienum eſſe ab inſtitutis meis ullum in medium addu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere patrem quin conceptis verbis propitium, <hi>Boil. p.</hi> 10.</note> would bring no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but what was expreſly for his Opinion, and uſe none but<note n="t" place="margin">Animo decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verim argumenta invictiſſima conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Arguments; but <hi>Roman</hi> Faith muſt be defended with <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> courage and confidence, which is the only invincible thing they have.</p>
            <p>The words of <hi>Theodoret</hi> are a great deal more plauſible, and ſeem at the firſt glance, to look more fairly, than any for their purpoſe. <hi>The Elements are underſtood to be what they are made, and they are believed and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, as thoſe things which they are believed</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theod. Dialog. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. apud <hi>Boil.</hi> p. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note>. Here our Faith makes the Sacrament to be what it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, to become to us the <hi>res Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti,</hi> as well as a ſign and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of it, and that thing is to be adored by us, in the uſe of the Sacrament, which is the true ſenſe of <hi>Theodorets</hi> words; and that he cannot mean in the <hi>Roman</hi> ſenſe, that the Elements are converted into another ſubſtance, the ſubſtance of Chriſts Body, is plain from what immediately goes before, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroys what they would catch from half his words; for he ſays, <hi>That the Elements, or the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Signs do not after ſanctification recede from their own, but remain in their former ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note>. Thus their beſt Witneſs, that ſeems to ſpeak the moſt for them, yet ſpeaks that againſt them, which deſtroys their whole cauſe, as he muſt own, whoever reads the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63797:27"/>Dialogue, and conſiders the deſign of it, which was to anſwer the pretence of thoſe, who ſaid that the Body of Chriſt was after his Aſcenſion, turned into a Divine ſubſtance, and loſt the true nature of Body<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, as the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols of Chriſts Body and Blood are changed, ſay thoſe Hereticks, into what they were not before, Yes ſaies he, <hi>Now ye are taken in your own net;</hi> for they remain in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer nature and ſubſtance afterwards, and ſo does Chriſts Body. If then the change of theſe ſacred Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be only as to <hi>their uſe</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> but not as to their <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> according to <hi>Theodoret,</hi> then he could not mean that they ſhould be adored, but only reverenced by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, juſt as the Holy Bible<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Liturg. Chryſoſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Acta Concil. Epheſ.</note>, is ſaid to be reverenced, and the Prieſt themſelves, by the very ſame word <hi>z.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Some of the Fathers words imply, that when we come to the Sacrament, it ſhould be with the greateſt lowlineſs, both of Body and Mind; and as the Primitive Church uſed to do, and as the Church of <hi>England</hi> does, in a poſture of Worſhip and Adoration, in the form and manner of Worſhip, as St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieroſ.</hi> ſpeaks<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch. Myſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, or as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, In the form of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicants and Worſhippers</hi>
               <note n="b" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chryſoſt. Homil. <hi>7.</hi> in Matth. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ibid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Homil. de Phil. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Homil. in c. <hi>10.</hi> Ep. <hi>1.</hi> ad Cor.</note> of Chriſt,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63797:28"/>as the <hi>Magi</hi> were, when they came to bring their preſents to him; <hi>do thou then preſent him with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and a lowly and ſubmiſſive heart, and be not like</hi> Herod, <hi>who pretended he would come to worſhip him, but it was to murder him; but rather imitate the</hi> Magi, <hi>and come with greater fear and reverente to thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our than they did.</hi> This is the whole deſign and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of what is produced out of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Boil. c. <hi>7.</hi> l <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, And this is the plain meaning of <hi>Origen</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 5. <hi>in N. T.</hi> Tunc Dominus ſub tectum tuum in greditur; tu ergo hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milians teipſum imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare hunc Centurio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; dicito, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine non ſum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ut intres ſub tectum meum.</note>, that when we come to receive Chriſt in the Sacrament, we ſhould do it with all Humility; for conſider, ſays he, <hi>That then the Lord enters under thy roof; do thou therefore humble thy ſelf, and imitate the Centurion, and ſay, Lord I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt enter under my roof.</hi> When the Fathers would give us the Picture of a devout Communicant, they draw him in the greateſt Poſture of Humility and Reverence, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon and<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Chryſoſtom in Serm. <hi>31.</hi> in natal Dom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Johan. Hieroſ. apud Chryſoſt. &amp; apud Boil. <hi>p. 44.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> adoring his Saviour, who died for him upon the Croſs, proſtrating his Soul, and his Body before him, and exerciſing the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt acts of Devotion to him, and with Tears in his Eyes and Sorrow in his heart, ſtanding like a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent before him, trembling and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63797:28"/>as ſenſible of his own guilt; with his Eyes caſt down, and with dejected Looks conſidering that he is but Duſt and Aſhes, who is vouchſafed to this Honour, and inwardly Groaning, and Sighing, and Panting in his Soul, ſaying, <hi>Lord I am not worthy, that thou ſhouldeſt enter under my roof;</hi> and the like. And thus they may find all devout Communicants in our Church behaving themſelves, during the whole Solemnity and Celebration of that bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which Myſtery they always adore Chriſt, and that Fleſh of Chriſt which was crucified; for then as St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeak, when their minds are all the while inflamed with the moſt devout Affections, and they are performing all the inward and outward Acts of the higheſt Devotion to God and their Saviour, then they are upon their Knees, offering up moſt ardent Prayers and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings; but not to the ſacred Symbols which are before them, or the Sacrament it ſelf as the object to which, but as the Circumſtance, at and in which all this Devotion and Worſhip is performed. And there is a great deal of difference from all this in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they direct all this to the Sacrament it ſelf, and to the conſecrated Elements, when they terminate their Worſhip upon what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and direct their Intentions to that as an Object; and therefore, whenever they have this Object appear to them, they immediately fall down and worſhip it, not only in the time of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when it finds them at their Devotion, but at all other times, when they are ſtanding or walking in the Streets, and are in no preſent Temper or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Devotion; yet all of a ſudden, as ſoon as they ſee the Hoſt coming by, they muſt put themſelves
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63797:29"/>into one, and Adore that very Object, that appears to them.</p>
            <p>The Fathers always ſpeak of Perſons as coming to the Sacrament, and partaking of it, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Chriſt, and the Body of Chriſt in the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Divine Myſteries; but it never enter'd into their minds or thoughts, to perſwade or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their hearers in their moſt devout Diſcourſes, to Adore the Hoſt, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in, or eſpecially out of the time of that ſacred So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity; and tho it be very eaſie to make a Book out of the Fathers, and to heap Authorities out of them to little purpoſe; yet, it is impoſible to prove by all the places produced out of them, by <hi>T. G.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> Of the Adoration of the bleſſed Sacrament.</note>, or more largely by <hi>Boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean,</hi> that they meant any more than what we are very willing to joyn with them in, that Chriſt is to be worſhipt in the Sacrament, as in Baptiſm, and the other Offices of our Religion; and that his Body and Fleſh, which he offered for us, and by which we expect Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is alſo to be adored, as being always united to his Divine Nature; and that the Sacrament it ſelf, as repreſenting the great Myſtery of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be highly reverenced by us, and that we ſhould come to receive it with all Humility, and in the moſt decent Poſture of Worſhip and Adoration, as the Primitive Chriſtians did. But that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf is to be adored, as well as Chriſt; that which the Prieſt holds in his hands, or lies upon the Altar before us, that this is to be the Object of our Worſhip, and to have all manner of <hi>Latria,</hi> both of Body and Soul directed to that, as to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; that the conſecrated Elements, or the ſacred
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63797:29"/>Symbols of Chriſts Body and Blood are to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt by us, when we receive them, or when with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out receiving them we ſee them ſet upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or carried about in Proceſſion; this, which is the Controverſie between us, not one Father ſays, but above three hundred of them together in a Council ſay<note n="g" place="margin">Concil. Sept. Conſtant. Act. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, <hi>That to prevent Idolatry, Chriſt appointed an excellent Image and Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf in the Sacrament, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of humane ſhape, even the plain and ſimple ſubſtance of Bread.</hi> But they reſolve that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry ſhall not be prevented, but they will be ſo ſottiſh as to commit it with that, which was deſigned to prevent it, and which one would think, ſhould not in the leaſt tempt any man to it, with a bit of Bread.</p>
            <p>The Abſurdities of which, upon a general view of the whole, I ſhall now for a Concluſion repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and offer as the laſt Argument againſt it, and tho that alone might be ſufficient, ſince God never impoſes any thing that is really fooliſh and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, to be believed or practiced by his Creatures; yet I thought it the fitteſt to be produced after we are well aſſured, that neither Scripture nor Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have required any ſuch thing. And however unwilling <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Bell de Sacram. Euchar. <hi>l. 3. c. 10.</hi>
               </note> is to admit of Arguments of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from the Abſurdity of the thing, as knowing how very liable the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was to them; and tho 'tis the moſt unjuſt Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon Chriſtianity to ſay, that any thing that is a part of that is ſo, which they are too ready to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, and ſo bring a reproach upon the common Chriſtianity, rather than part with their own ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63797:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Opinions; yet after we have thoroughly imformed our ſelves, that there is nothing of a Divine Authority, as one can hardly think there ſhould be for what is ſo abſurd in it ſelf, then an Argument from the folly and unreaſonableneſs of the thing, muſt be allowed to be very proper; and till men have loſt all their Reaſon, it will always be very cogent; and here it is ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong, and preſſes ſo hard upon their Adoration of the Hoſt, that 'tis no wonder that they love to ſet by, and except againſt reaſon, whenever this matter is to be tryed: but it is moſt ſad to conſider, that they ſhould have ſo little regard and concern for the Credit and Reputation of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as by this means ſo ſhamefully and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to expoſe it to the Reproach and Contempt of the wiſeſt Men. How muſt a <hi>Jew</hi> or a <hi>Turk,</hi> who are great enemies to all Idolatry, be prejudiced againſt Chriſtianity, when he ſees thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, fall down and worſhip a Wafer, and make an Idol of a bit of Bread? When he lives in thoſe places, where he ſees it carried about with Candles and Torches before it, in moſt Solemn and Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Proceſſions, and all Perſons as it goes by, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon their Knees, and ſaying their prayers, and uſing all acts of Devotion to it; would he not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what ſtrange and new God, that no Hiſtory ever mention'd, the Chriſtians adored?</p>
            <p>Mankind indeed, when very ignorant, uſed to worſhip a great many Creatures that were very uſeful to them, and when they were very hungry, if they lighted upon Bread, it was no great wonder; but ſure it can be no more fit to be worſhipt by thoſe who bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter know God, than any of his other Creatures, or any of the moſt dumb and ſenſeleſs, and pitiful Images, for which the Chriſtians ſo often, and ſo juſtly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63797:30"/>laught at the Idolatrous Heathens; eſpecially, thoſe of them, who were ſo fooliſh, and ſuch true belly-Gods, as to eat and feed upon what they worſhipt and deified. This the firſt and moſt learned Chriſtians charged, as the higheſt degree of folly in the <hi>Egyptians, to eat the ſame Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, whom they worſhipt</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Orig contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> I. 4 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tatian. Orat. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Graec.</hi> A pim bovem adoratis &amp; paſcitis Minut. <hi>Octav.</hi> p. 94.</note>; And a wiſe Heathen could not <hi>think any would be ſo mad as to think that to be a God, with which he was fed</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ecquem tam amentem eſſe putas, ut illud quo veſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Denm eſſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat? <hi>Tally de natura Deorum.</hi>
               </note>. It was the ingenious Opinion of a very learned Father, that God made the difference between the clean and unclean Beaſt, to prevent this <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> and Brutiſh folly in the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> who lived among them; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>by their abominating the unclean, they would not deifie them; and by eating the clean, they would be ſecured from ever worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them; for it muſt be the extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt madneſs to worſhip what they eat</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret. in Quaeſt. in Geneſ.</note>. How did the Ancient Apologiſts for Chriſtianity with great wit and ſmartneſs, ridicule the other Idols of the Heathens, as being the works at firſt of the Carver, or the Painter, and particularly for being ſuch Gods as were baked at firſt in the Furnace<note n="m" place="margin">Incoctos for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacibus figulinis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nob. contra Gent. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> of the Potter (and it had been much the ſame, had it been in the Oven of the Baker) for being Gods of Braſs, or of Silver<note n="n" place="bottom">Deus aereus vel argenteus, <hi>Minut. Octav.</hi> p. 74</note>? And
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63797:31"/>yet they counted the Silver or the Braſs no more a God<note n="o" place="margin">Nos neque aeris neque auri argenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que materias, <hi>Arnob. ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> than others do the Bread, as I have ſhown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. How at other times did they think ſit to expoſe their impotent and ſenſeleſs Deities, becauſe they could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves from Thieves<note n="p" place="margin">Deos veſtros plerumque in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam furibus cedere Lactant. <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> l. 2. c. 4.</note>, nor yet from rotteneſs; but the Worms would ſtill gnaw, and the Vermine deface them, and the Birds would defile them with their excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments even in their own Temples<note n="q" place="margin">Quanto verius de diis veſtris ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia muta natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter judicant, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, hirundines, mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi; non ſentire eos ſciunt, rodunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultant, inſident, ac niſi abigatis, in ipſo Dei veſtri ore nidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant; Araneae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro faciem ejus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texunt, <hi>Minut. Octav.</hi> p. 75.</note>? And could not this be ſaid of a breaden Deity? is not that as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to all theſe miſchances, and therefore as liable to all thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches? will not a Mouſe or Rat run away with it? tho if it do ſo, they have taken care, if they can catch the ſacrilegious Thief, to have the Sacrament drawn out of its entrails, and religiouſly diſpoſed of<note n="r" place="margin">Antonin. de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Miſſ. in Biſhop <hi>Jewels</hi> reply.</note>; but however, if no ſuch mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune come to it, it will in a little time, if it be kept, prove ſowre, and grow mouldy; and when it does ſo, what ſhould then thruſt out the Deity, and bring in again the ſubſtance of the Bread that was quite gone before, is an unaccountable Miracle; and that which is taken of it into our Bodies, is not like one would think to have any better, or more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming treatment there, than by the other ways; ſo that upon all theſe accounts, this which is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by Chriſtians, is in as ill Condition as that which was worſhipped by Heathens; and thoſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63797:31"/>Adverſaries, <hi>Celſus,</hi> and <hi>Porphyry,</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi> would have thrown all that the Chriſtians had ſaid againſt the Heathen Idols, back upon themſelves, and have improved them with as great Advantage, and retorted them with as much force, had the Chriſtians in thoſe times worſhipt the Hoſt, or the Sacramental Elements, as the Papiſts do now; and 'tis more than a Preſumption, no leſs than a Demonſtration that the Chriſtians did not, becauſe none of theſe things that were ſo obnoxious, and ſo obvious, were ever in the leaſt mentioned by the Heathens, or made matter of Reflection upon them, when they pickt up all other things, let them be true or falſe, that they could make any uſe of to object againſt them. But the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians gave them no ſuch occaſion; which was the only Reaſon they did not take it. As ſoon as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did ſo, by ſetting up the worſhip of the Hoſt<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apud Dionyſ. Carthus in</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> Nullam ſe ſectam Chriſtiana dererio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem aut ineptiorem reperire.</p>
                  <p>Quem colunt Deum, dentibus ipſi ſuis diſcerpunt ac devorant.</p>
               </note>, <hi>Averroes</hi> the <hi>Arabian</hi> Philoſopher, in the <hi>13th</hi> Century, gave this Character of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that he had found <hi>no Sect more fooliſh, or worſe than they,</hi> in all his Travels and Obſervations, upon this very account, <hi>For they eat the God whom they worſhip;</hi> and<note n="t" place="margin">Bullaeus Gultius in Itin. <hi>Mange Dieu.</hi>
               </note> a later Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian and Traveller tells us, that 'tis a common Reproach in the Mouths of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> to call the Chriſtians <hi>Devourers of their God;</hi> and a <hi>Jew,</hi> in a Book Printed at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in the year 1662, among other Queſtions put to Chriſtians, asks this ſhrewd one, <hi>If the Hoſt be a God, why does it corrupt and grow covered with Mold? and why is it gnawn by Mice or other Animals</hi>
               <note n="v" place="bottom">Si Hoſtia Deus eſt cur ſitu obducta corrumpitur? curagliribus &amp; umribus correditur? <hi>Lib. quaeſt. &amp; Reſp.</hi>
               </note>?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:63797:32"/>
The only way the Papiſts have to bring themſelves off from theſe manifeſt Abſurdities, is only a running farther into greater; and their little Shifts and Evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are ſo thin and ſubtil Sophiſtry, or rather ſuch groſs and thick falſhoods, that it could not be imagined that the Heathen Adverſaries could ever know them, and therefore be ſo civil as <hi>Boileau</hi> would make them<note n="a" place="margin">Cap. <hi>10.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> de ador. Euch.</note>, as not to lay thoſe charges upon them, as others do; nor can any reaſonable and impartial man ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them; for they are plainly theſe two; That they do not worſhip what all the World ſees they worſhip; And that they do not eat what they take into their Mouths and ſwallow down: Which is in plain words an open Confeſſion, that they are aſhamed to own what they plainly do; We do not worſhip the Bread, ſay they, for that we believe is done away, and turned into the natural Body of Chriſt, and ſo we cannot be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with Bread-worſhip. But do ye not worſhip that which ye ſee, and which ye have before ye, and which is carried about? And would not any man that ſees what that is, think ye worſhip Bread or Wafer? And could you ever perſwade him, that it was any thing elſe? And if notwithſtanding what you think of it againſt all Senſe and Reaſon, it be ſtill Bread; then I hope it is Bread that ye worſhip; and till others think as wildly as ye do, ye muſt give them leave to think and charge ye thus. But if it were true, that ye did not worſhip the Bread, yet ye muſt and do own, that ye worſhip the Species of the Bread; and how ye ſhould do that, without being guilty of another very groſs Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, ye do not know your ſelves; for ye muſt make them ſo united to Chriſt, as to make one <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> and ſo one Object of Worſhip, as his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63797:32"/>and Godhead are; and then according to this way of yours, Chriſt may as well be ſaid to be Impanated and United to Bread, or its Species, as Incarnated and United to Fleſh, as ſome of you have taught<note n="w" place="margin">Bellarm. de Ruperto Abbate Tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienſi, <hi>l. 3.</hi> de Euch. <hi>c. 11.</hi>
               </note> that the Bread in the Euchariſt is aſſumed by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the humane Nature was. But not to mention theſe, which whereſoever ye turn ye, ſtare ye full in the face, and ſhould make ye bluſh, one would think, had ye not put off all ſhame, as well as all ſenſe in this matter; grant ye what ye would have, that it is not Bread, but the ſubſtantial Body, Fleſh and Blood of a man, that is in the Hoſt; will this help much to mend the matter, or to leſſen the Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not rather increaſe and ſwell it? For beſides the incredible wonder, that a bit of Bread ſhould by a few words of every common Prieſt, be turned immediately into the true and perfect Body of a man; nav, into ten thouſand Bodies at the ſame time, which is a greater Miracle than ever was done i'th' World, and is as great almoſt, as creating the World it ſelf out of nothing; and if it were true, would make ſhe Prieſt a God, certainly, and not a man, and much rather to be worſhipt than a bit of Bread, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaies of the Heathen Idols, <hi>He that made them, ought rather to be worſhip than they</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Meliorem eſſe qui fecit, quam illa quae facta ſunt &amp; ſi haec adoranda ſunt, artificem a quo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſunt, ipſum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que multo potiori jure adorandum eſſe. <hi>Lactant. Inſtit.</hi> l. 2. c. 2.</note>. Beſides this, it ſeems it is the whole Body of a man, then, which is eaten and ſwallowed down, inſtead of Bread; for ſure the ſame thing is not one thing when it is worſhipt, and another thing when it is eaten; and then how barbarous and inhumane, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63797:33"/>well as abſurd and ridiculous, muſt this appear to any man, that is not uſed to ſwallow the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Nonſenſe, as well as the whole Body of a man for a Morſel? and then all the former Abſurdities which I mentioned, do return again, of the Eating that which we worſhip, which the <hi>Apologiſts</hi> thought ſo wild and extravagant in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> God eaters. Well then, there is no other way, but to ſay, we don't eat him as we eat other food<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boil c.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 2. Comeſtionem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae corporis Chriſti non eſſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalem.</note>; ſo might the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> have ſaid too, if they had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; tho, how they can otherwiſe eat him, 'tis hard to underſtand; but only in the heretical ſenſe of Spiritual and Sacramental Eating; unleſs they will at the ſame time ſay, <hi>They do not eat him truly and naturally, and yet do eat him ſo;</hi> and they are ſo uſed to Contradictions in this point, that I don't know whether they will make any more Bones of this, than of the reſt, or of the ſubſtantial Body of a man himſelf, when they have got ſo large a Faith, or rather ſo large a Swallow. But how is it, that ye do not eat him after a natural and carnal manner, and yet it is a carnal Body, that ye ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, and that ye really and truly eat, and 'tis a Carnal mouth and throat he is put into, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a very foul and wicked one? And yet this muſt by this carnal way eat the very Body of Chriſt, as well as the moſt faithful; <hi>But we do not grind this Body with our Teeth, nor chew him in our Mouths, as our other Food; nor digeſt him in our Stomachs, nor caſt him out into the draught;</hi> if ye do not as ye pretend, being aſhamed of the moſt ſhameful and abominable Conſequences of it; and yet a very
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63797:33"/>great many among you, have owned all that<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Retract. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reng. ſub Nicol.</hi> 2 <hi>in Concil. Rom.</hi> Verum corpus Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri Jeſu Chriſti ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiter, non ſolum Sacramento, ſed in veritate, manibus Sacerdotum tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri &amp; frangi &amp; fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium dentibus atteri, <hi>Sic Gualt. &amp; Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baud apud. Boil.</hi> p. 177.</note>, as not knowing how it could be otherwiſe, and how if this eating be Spiritual and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, Chriſts preſence may not be ſo too, which is the Hereſie on the other ſide<note n="a" place="margin">Iſte in omnibus veritatem ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit, dum aſſerit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia fieri (ſc. fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem &amp; attritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem corporis Chriſti in Euchariſtia) non ſubſtantia ſed in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie viſibili &amp; forma panis &amp; Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tantum. <hi>Gualter adverſus Abailard. apud Boil.</hi> 179.</note>; and ye ſeem to make ſtrange Monſters of your ſelves that have ſpiritual Teeth, and can ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and not naturally eat a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and a carnal Body; and if ye do not thus eat it, as ye eat other meat, when ye take it into your Mouths, and into your Stomacks, and do every thing to it that you do to your other food, which is as like eating as if it were very true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural eating; and if it be not Bread, which is thus eaten, when it is juſt as like other Bread as is poſſible, then it is certainly, the moſt phantaſtick Food, and the moſt phantaſtick way of eating it, that can be imagined; then there muſt be a new way of eating, which is not eating, and a new way for a Body to be preſent, and yet not preſent as a Body; and I will add there muſt certainly be then a new underſtanding, which is no underſtanding, that can underſtand, or believe all this.</p>
            <p>But further, ye have found it neceſſary for your purpoſe of Adoring the Hoſt, to keep the Body of Chriſt confined to it, and incloſed in it as a Priſoner, till the Species corrupt, and ſo the priſon is as it were opened, and the Body let looſe, and when that is gone, whether ye think it be the Species, or the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63797:34"/>of Bread that corrupts, I would gladly know; and ſurely then, when the Body is gone, there is no need of ſuch a miracle to keep the Accidents with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Subject; if it be Bread, what think ye of this ſudden Tranſmutation from Bread to Fleſh, and from Fleſh to Bread again, and this latter without any words from the Prieſt; but ſince Chriſts Body muſt be ſo permanently in the Hoſt, not only in the act and uſe of the Sacrament, but at all other times; ye are then forced to own, that as it is eaten in the Communion, as well by thoſe who have no faith, as by the moſt faithful Chriſtians, ſo if any other Animals ſhould happen to eat the Hoſt, taking it no doubt heretically for meer Bread, that yet they truly take the Body of Chriſt, and eat it after ſome manner or other, but whether it be after a natural manner in them or no, I don't know how you have reſolved, but moſt of the Schoolmen have agreed that Scandalous queſtion<note n="b" place="margin">An mus, vel Porcus vel canis comedens hoſtiam ſuſcipit corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti? <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewels <hi>reply Artic.</hi> 24. <hi>See</hi> Burchard <hi>de Correct. Miſſ. upon thoſe Queſtions,</hi> De vino in calice congelato, de muſca vel aranea vel veneno mixto cum ſanguine, de vomitu poſt recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Sacramenti, Quando cadit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti, Quando cadit ſanguis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. <hi>fol.</hi> 51, 52.</note> in the Affirmative, <hi>Whether if a Mouſe, or a Hog, or a Dog eat the Hoſt, they do partake of Chriſts Body?</hi> Or as <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> your moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelick Doctor ſays, conſequently to this Opinion of yours<note n="c" place="margin">Aliter deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret veritati-corporis Chriſti. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>qu.</hi> 79.</note>, <hi>It would otherwiſe derogate from the truth of this Sacrament and Chriſts preſence in it.</hi> So that wherever the Species are, there is always Chriſts Body, and whatever happens to them, happens to that alſo; If they fall to the ground, Chriſts Body does ſo to; and ſo, if they lie in a hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Tooth, or hang but in the leaſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63797:34"/>crum or drop upon a Communicants Beard; there according to their principles, they and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt be worſhipt with <hi>Latria;</hi> and if they be in a Mouſe or Flies body, that has got to them, the adorable Object ſtill goes with the Species, till they be corrupted; and whither the Species be corrupted, or no if they be poyſoned as they have ſomtimes been, or whether Chriſt be there with the Accidents of the Poyſon, I can't tell; but when the Species are in the pix, he is as faſt there, as he ever was in his Sepulcher, and to all appearance as dead and ſenſeleſs, and if the Species be Burnt or Gnawn, or vomited out of the Stomack, before they are corrupted, all theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes belong as truly to Chriſts Body as to them, and ſo worſe indignities may be thus offered every day to Chriſt glorious Body, than ever were offered to it, in its ſtate of Humility and Contempt upon Earth, when it was Spit upon, and Scourged, and Pierced, and Crucified by the <hi>Jews.</hi> But Good God! that men ſhould think to Honour and Adore Chriſt and his Body, by thus expoſing them to the danger of the vileſt Abuſes! that humane reaſon ſhould be ſo decayed and beſotted, as to believe and defend ſuch palpable Abſurdities! that Chriſtianity ſhould be ſo ſhamefully and abominably expoſed to all the World, by ſuch an extravagant Doctrine, and ſuch an obnoxious practice and unreaſonable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as this is? God Almighty open all our Eyes, that we may not be given up to <hi>blindneſs</hi> of Mind, and <hi>darkneſs</hi> of Underſtanding, and to the <hi>belief</hi> of Lies, as moſt Idolaters generally were; <hi>but may it pleaſe him,</hi> who is the God of Truth, <hi>to bring into the way of Truth, all ſuch as have erred and are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63797:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>deceived,</hi> in this or any other matter; in which charitable and conſtant Prayer of our Church, which is much better than Curſing and Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, its Adverſaries, I hope, as well as its Friends will not refuſe to joyn with it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere are ſeveral miſtakes of the Preſs, but moſt of them are ſo Plain and Obvious, that it is hoped that every Reader will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſee and correct them without any trouble, and without any particular account of them.</p>
            <p>Five Sermons of Contentment, one of Patience, and one of Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Will of God, By <hi>Iſaac Barrow,</hi> D. D. late Maſter of <hi>Trinity Colledg</hi> in <hi>Cambridg.</hi> Never Publiſhed before; in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
